<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A touch-stone for a Christian Wherein is shewed, how a man may know, whether he be the Temple of the Holy Ghost, hath a sauing faith, be the childe of God, hath truly repented, and (in one word) be a Christian in deed, or in name onely. By Thomas Broade.</title>
            <author>Broad, Thomas, 1577 or 8-1635.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16916</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852577_17903</idno>
  <idno type="VID">17903</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264191279</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 3807_pt1</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S117363</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99852577e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16916)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17903)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1228:08, 1299:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A touch-stone for a Christian Wherein is shewed, how a man may know, whether he be the Temple of the Holy Ghost, hath a sauing faith, be the childe of God, hath truly repented, and (in one word) be a Christian in deed, or in name onely. By Thomas Broade.</title>
                  <author>Broad, Thomas, 1577 or 8-1635.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 156, [4]; [4], 101, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Melchisedech Bradwood for Thomas Hauiland, and are to be sold at his shop in Gilt-spurre street without Newgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts; the second part, "A Christians vvarre", has separate dated title page and pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 is identified as STC 3805 on UMI microfilm, reel 1299.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1228 (part 1 only) and at reel 1299 (part 2 only).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Anglican authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17903:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17903:1"/>
            <p>A TOVCH-STONE FOR A CHRISTIAN: Wherein is shewed, HOW A MAN MAY KNOW, whether he be the Temple of the Holy Ghost, hath a sauing faith, be the childe of God, hath truly repented, and (in one word) be a Christian in deed, or in name onely.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS BROADE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. COR. 3. 16.</bibl>
               <p>Know ye not, that ye are the Temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. COR. 13. 5.</bibl>
               <p>Prooue your selues, whether you are in the faith▪ examine your selues.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>CYPRIAN. lib. 2. epist. 2.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Accipe quod sentitur, antequam discitur▪</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Melchisedech Bradwood</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Thomas Hauiland,</hi> and are to be sold at his shop in Gilt-spurre street without Newgate. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17903:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17903:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir <hi>William Killygrew,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Killygrew,</hi> and to the vertuous Ladies their wiues: <hi>Increase of wisedome and fauour with God and man.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worshipfull, you shall rightly so bee called, if you worship God aright: And thus you doe vndoubtedly, if you worship him <hi>in Spirit and truth:</hi> for the Father re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth such worshippers. But thus for certaine you
<pb facs="tcp:17903:3"/> cannot doe, vnlesse his <hi>Spirit dwelleth</hi> in you; which I hope it doth <hi>plentifully,</hi> and pray it may still more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, vntill you come to dwell with God in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. The kinde entertainment I once found in your house, makes me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted more than I am able to discharge: my God that dwelleth in his house, I meane, <hi>your bodies,</hi> repay it ten fold into your bosomes, or hearts rather; for the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some receiueth the transito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but the heart the <hi>true treasure;</hi> &amp; God (you know) dwelleth within, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his holy Temple.</p>
            <p>This Temple of God, your bodies, giue me leaue to put
<pb facs="tcp:17903:3"/> you in minde (though not inmindfull already) to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orne on the inside in the best manner, that so the glorious beautie thereof being seene of men, it may redound to the praise and glorie of the builder and housholder: for it is strange to see the folly of many in this last and worst age of the world, who take great paines &amp; bestow much cost in beautifying the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side vntill it euen shine again with gold &amp; pretious stones. The fashion now adaies is changed euery day, and yet they can neuer light vpon the right fashion. For the Temple was couered with lead on the outside, and on the inside was ouerlaid with
<pb facs="tcp:17903:4"/> pure gold. It were good then for those which are couered with gold, and are so glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous without, to beware lest within they bee ouerlaied with lead, or such like base metall. Doe men vse to paint Churches on the out-side, where the winde and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would soone cause the colour to fade away? Let the <hi>hid man of the heart</hi> be trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vp in the best manner, paint heere as much as you will, spare no paines, spare no cost, let it be done in colours of gold, vntill you shine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine as lights in the middest of a froward generation: this is a pretious thing in the sight of that God which dwelleth in you.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17903:4"/>
            <p>As a token of my loue and vnfained affection, I heere present you with the <hi>First-fruits</hi> of my labours: <hi>First-fruits</hi> I call them, but in that sense happily as Christ was Maries <hi>First-borne,</hi> when as she neuer had other childe. If you kindly accept hereof, I haue part of my desire: if you and others profit heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, I haue all, and God too (I trust) who set mee on worke; for he <hi>willeth not the death of a sinner,</hi> and I would not be <hi>a sauour of death</hi> vnto any. My hearty praier then vnto this our gracious God is, so to blesse this little mite cast into the Treasurie for the repairing of his house, that it may helpe to build
<pb facs="tcp:17903:5"/> you vp daily more &amp; more, vntill you reach to the <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Ierusalem;</hi> where I hope in Christ our Sauiour to dwell with you once againe, and world without end. God send vs a ioifull mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. In the meane time, whiles I liue, I will rest</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worships in all dutie, Thomas Broade.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17903:5"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orasmuch as all men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most perswade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, that they are led by the Spirit of God, and are indeed Christs faithfull Disciples: howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the Spirit hath spoken euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <note place="margin">1. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that in the latter times iniquitie shall abound; and Christ himselfe complaining of these daies, hath said, <note place="margin">Luk. 18.</note>
               <hi>When the Sonne of man commeth, shall he finde faith on the earth?</hi> I haue therfore thought it labour not ill bestowed, if I could teach thee (gentle Reader) how thou mightest know, and not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued,
<pb facs="tcp:17903:6"/> whether thou art indeede such a one, as most men vainly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine themselues to be. If thou art a strong Christian, I need not teach it thee, as one that knoweth it already. But I haue written for the weake Christians sake, that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue comfort, and be strengthned heereby: as also that the carelesse Christian awaking out of his sleepe of securitie, <note place="margin">Ephes. 5.</note> and standing vp from the dead, Christ might giue vnto him the light of his holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>Now, whereas this my discourse is not fraught with out landish words, and filed phrases, such as are in great request amongst many: if by my plainnesse I shall bee offensiue vnto any, my Apologie for my selfe is briefly thus. <note place="margin">Act. 18.</note> Apollos was an elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent man, as Saint Luke testifieth of him: and I see very many in all places, which in this point hold of Apollos. <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> Paul shewed no such elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, as he himselfe saith of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe:
<pb facs="tcp:17903:6"/> and it were not (I thinke) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse, that some in some places should hold of Paul also. And then, if Paul doth first plant, and Apollos afterward with his sweet showres of eloquence doth water; there is great cause to hope, that God will giue greater increase, than hitherto hee hath done in many places. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, there are too few in these daies which hold of Paul. Either we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not plant, nor teach the plaine truth plainly: or if we can, straight we goe to watering, and striue to shew our eloquence. But God of his mercie send vs some such as Paul into his vineyard, which may plant, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour more than they all: for vnlesse planting goe before watering, this kind of watering shall doe little good; <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> especially seeing not many wise men after the flesh, but God hath chosen the foolish things of the world to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the wise.</p>
            <p>Surely, when I first left the Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersitie,
<pb facs="tcp:17903:7"/> before I might publikely so doe, I beganne to instruct some pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately: and it is altogether incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, how hardly they receiued euen milke, giuen also in the most easie and familiar manner that I could deuise. Since this time I haue bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den eloquence farewell: and mine only endeuour, and earnest praier, hath beene; that I might truly say with the Apostle, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 11.</note>
               <hi>Though I bee rude in speaking, yet am I not so in knowledge.</hi> I hold of S. Paul▪ I would be exceeding plaine: for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, I seeke not to please thee with newfangled words and curious phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, whereby I should become a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barian vnto some; <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 14.</note> but to haue thee please God with thy good works and plaine dealing, that so thou maist be accounted a good Christian of all. Bring not then any such mind to the reading of this Treatise: but seeing it teacheth a matter of greatest mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in these our carelesse daies,
<pb facs="tcp:17903:7"/> reade it with good deliberation, ad in any wise beware of flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy selfe. Truly, if thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest make a good vse heereof, I nothing doubt, but ere it were long, thou shouldest learne one good les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, which many great Doctours shall neuer bee able to learne; namely, that thou thy selfe shalt be saued. Happie is hee that hath learned this lesson perfectly, and by heart: it will not a little reioice that mans heart euer after. This happinesse (gentle Reader) God of his mercie will grant vnto thee, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse thou art mercilesse towards thy selfe, and louest thine owne mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Account it as a sure token of Gods goodwill, whensoeuer he brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a good booke vnto thine hands: and if thou wouldest not haue this token of his good will become a meanes of his greater displeasure, reade attentiuely, meditate dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently,
<pb facs="tcp:17903:8"/> pray continually. Reade, meditate, pray, and God shall giue a blessing.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
               <signed>Thomas Broade.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17903:8"/>
            <head>A Touch-stone, WHEREBY a good Christian may be knowen from a Counterfet.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. Of the fall of our first parents, and the miserable seruitude of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde vnder sinne and Satan by meanes thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD hauing afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand prouided all things needful for the vse of man, formed Adams body of the dust of the earth, and breathed in his face the breath
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17903:9"/> of life. Who being thus made God took (as the Scripture saith) <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 15.</note> and put in the garden of Eden. So then, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Adam made out of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise.</hi>
                  </note> by right of creation A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam could not challenge Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise for an habitation: only that which placed him in the earthly Paradise, is the same, which shall place vs in the heauenly, namely, the free mercie of God. At this time man was in blessed estate: for being made after the likenes of his maker (a better patterne than which, I doe not know) hee had all things put vnder his feet, <note place="margin">Psal. 8.</note>
                  <hi>All sheepe and oxen, yea and the beasts of the field, the fowles of the aire, and the fish of the sea, and that which passeth thorow the pathes of the seas.</hi> In a word, God made him to haue dominion ouer the workes of his hands: but yet, to the end he might know himselfe to be vnder his Creator, howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer hee were aboue the other
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17903:9"/> creatures, it pleased God to giue him a Law, and to forbid him the eating of one tree in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, called by name <hi>the tree of knowledge of good and euill;</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting him neuerthelesse freely to eat of al the rest, among which was the tree of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Of the tree of life.</hi>
                  </note> The tree of life (as it is thought) was so called, either because the fruit of it would preserue a mans life, as medicines doe: or else, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it was a signe only vnto A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam; that whiles he did eat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hee should liue. And to this opinion of the two I rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline: for there is no more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, wherefore I should thinke, that this tree would preserue a mans life, than the other would cause him to know good &amp; euill, which no man (that I know) doth imagine. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Of the tree of the knowledge of good and euill.</hi>
                  </note> The tree of the knowledge of good and euill (as it is thought) was so called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17903:10"/> it was a signe vnto our first parents, that whensoeuer they did eat thereof, they should pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure vnto themselues the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and euill: but what is meant by these words, I haue not certainly to affirme. Some are of opinion, that the tree of knowledge of good and euill, is all one with the tree of wisdome, according as Iosephus calleth it? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Antiq. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> But true wisdome (it seemeth) Adam neuer wanted before his fall: for Christ the second Adam came to restore that, which wee lost by the first; and wee see, that such as being truly regenerate, doe most resemble Adam in his state of innocencie, of all others are most godly wise, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore most truly wise. Surely, God made man at the first like vnto himselfe, and if in other things, no doubt in wisdome too: but when man, not content with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17903:10"/> Gods workmanship, would needs make himselfe after his likenesse; we finde, that God clothed him in beasts skinnes, as indeed being now become more like vnto them: for <hi>euery man</hi> (saith the Prophet) <note place="margin">Ier. 10. 14.</note>
                  <hi>is a beast by his owne knowledge.</hi> This exposition then I can by no meanes allow: and for mine owne part I rather thinke, that by the knowledge of good and euill, is meant the knowledge or experience of happinesse and miserie; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Or else: That it was good to obey God; and euill, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey him.</hi>
                  </note> as, that Adam and Eue, who before knew what happinesse was, and had experience thereof, should after their eating know what mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serie was, and haue experience thereof likewise. In this sense good and euill are vsually taken: and we finde, that presently after their eating, <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 7.</note>
                  <hi>the eies of them both were opened, and they knew that they were naked.</hi> The knowledge
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17903:11"/> then, which our first parents pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cured vnto themselues, was, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they were naked, and in a shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and miserable estate. Thus now the tree of knowledge of good and euill, is all one with the tree of death: and indeed God told them plainly, that whenso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they did eat thereof, they should die the death; and not in obscure termes, that they should know good and euill. But the reason, wherefore it pleased God to call it the tree of knowledge of good and euill, rather than the tree of death (as hee did call the other plainly, the tree of life) may be, that so hee might make greater triall of their obedience: for otherwise they would neuer haue beene perswaded, that by eating they should haue gotten any good; whereas now they were in hope of obtaining some great matter thereby. Neither
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17903:11"/> are we to thinke, that God then was the cause of their sinne, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee did not call it the tree of death, and moreouer made it pleasant to the sight, and placed it in the middest of the garden neere to the tree of life <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 9.</note> (for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the forbidden fruit was not only pleasant to their eies, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in their eies too, euen as it is likewise now a daies with vs:) no more, than if a master hauing laid a purse of gold in some open place, should be the cause of his seruants sinne, if he did steale it; for the master did it to make tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of his seruant, and so did God of his seruants Adam and Eue, which our owne reason being iudge he might well doe. For o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, since Adams eating of the tree of knowledge of good and euill, wee are become so wise in our own conceits, that vnlesse wee know a reason of Gods do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17903:12"/> we will hardly be perswaded that hee was altogether blame<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lesse, especially in this matte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which we haue in hand, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the fall of our first parents▪ Now, that which I thinke of both the trees, is briefly thus▪ The tree of life was so called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it was a signe vnto them, that whiles they did eat thereof, they should liue: but their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in keeping Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and not any vertue in the tree, was the cause that they should liue. Againe, the tree of knowledge of good and euill, or in plainer termes (as I thinke) the tree of death, was a signe vnto them, that when they did eat thereof, they should die: but their disobedience in breaking Gods commandement, and not any thing in the tree, was the cause of their miserie and death.</p>
               <p>Of this tree (as thou hast
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17903:12"/> heard) God forbade them to eat: but the Deuill, partly (as it seemeth) enuying their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; partly bearing them no good will, because they resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled God his vtter aduersarie; <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 1.</note> tempted the woman by word of mouth, as hee did our Sauiour Christ <note place="margin">Matt. 4. 3.</note> (for before sinne he could not happily suggest euil thoghts to her minde) and that he might the sooner preuaile, spake in a serpent vnto her. Some are of opinion▪ that it was not a serpent indeed, and that by this name the Deuill himselfe is meant, whom elsewhere we finde called an <hi>old serpent.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 12.</note> But their opinion I cannot approoue, and that for these reasons. First, because it is said; <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 1.</note>
                  <hi>The serpent was wiser than any beast of the field, which the Lord God had made.</hi> For to speake thus of the Deuill would seeme very strange: and as concerning
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17903:13"/> the wisdome of this beast aboue others, wee haue that saying in the Gospell, <note place="margin">Matt. 10.</note>
                  <hi>Be ye wise as serpents, and innocent as doues.</hi> Secondly, God telleth the serpent, that hee shall <hi>go vpon his bellie,</hi> as we know his seed doth: and moreouer, shall <hi>eat dust,</hi> (such as Adams bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die was made of) which seemeth to be serpents food, <note place="margin">Mic. 7. 17.</note>
                  <hi>They shall licke the dust like a serpent.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is said, <hi>Hee shall wound thine head, &amp; thou shalt wound his heele.</hi> Which words, howsoeuer they haue a mysticall signification, and are a prophecie of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Christ; yet may they also (I thinke) bee literally vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood: for the serpent being set to goe on his belly, is ready pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared as it were to hurt a mans heele, comming for feare priuily behinde him; and a man with his foot to tread vpon his head, as who can master him, though
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17903:13"/> his comming be knowen. A ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent then it was, I am fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suaded: and if any doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Deuill were the chiefe Agent in this businesse, seeing there is no mention made of him; let them consider that the Scripture attributeth vnto him the destruction of mankind, and for this cause (as I take it) our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour calleth him <hi>a murtherer from the beginning.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> Againe, the serpent speaketh, and in such sort, as if he had the vse of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: which of himselfe (I thinke) he could not, no more than Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams asse could; <note place="margin">Num. 22 <hi>It is worth the noting that the Deuill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused the wisest bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> to tempt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> sinne: an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> God vsed the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plest bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> to reprou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> for sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
                  </note> for we do not read, that God tooke away either his speech or his reason, and yet none of his seed can so much as speake. Moreouer, no creature (I thinke) bare man euill will: and God saith, that they were all very good. But this serpent tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pteth man to sinne, and also be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17903:14"/> God himselfe: for <hi>God knoweth</hi> (saith he) <hi>that yee shall be as Gods.</hi> Whereas contrariwise God knew, that they should be as Deuils: but this was, to the end they might haue a bad opinion of him, as though knowing the fruit to be good for them, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice he forbad them to eat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, lest happily they should be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to himselfe. These reasons haue induced me to thinke (as before I said) that the Deuill spake in a serpent: and if a Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>A Rauen saluted the people of Rome.</hi> Plin. lib. 19.</note> Parret, or the like being taught, can so mooue his tongue, as that hee vttereth plainly some sentences: wherefore should it seem an hard matter for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil being a spirit, so to mooue the tongue of the serpent, as that it should speake, what hee would haue it? Againe, it must not seem very strange, though God gaue the Deuill so much power ouer
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17903:14"/> the serpent, that whereas by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe he tempted Christ, by it he should tempt the woman: for we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee, that hee daily abuseth Gods good creatures to the same end, though not in the same manner. God suffered not the Deuill to cause the serpent to sting man, or any wayes to hurt him; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>To tempt, is not to hurt: for Christ was tempted, but not hurt.</hi> 1. Cor. 15</note> for God bare a fauour vnto Adam, as bearing his owne image: and whereas by means of the serpent <hi>the sting of death</hi> was fastned in him, he himselfe was wholly to blame; for Adam might haue resisted the temptation, howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the other, being without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and not knowing what hee did, could not chuse but tempt. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>It was not sin in the serpent, wanting reason, to tempt: no more, than it was a vertue in the asse to reproue. Vertue and vice befall not beasts.</hi>
                  </note> If any heere aske: wherfore then was God angry with the serpent? I answer, that if I had a Parret, which being taught, did speake blasphemous words against God; though I were more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17903:15"/> with his instructer, yet could I not be well pleased with him; and though hee knew not what he spake, yet would I cause his head to be pulled off, thereby to shew my hatred towards blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie. Moreouer, Gods iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are a depth without bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome: <note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> hath not the Potter power ouer the clay, to dispose of it at his pleasure? Pry not then too curiously into Gods wayes, for they are past finding out: and know this for certaine, that the Iudge of all the world will doe right vnto euery creature.</p>
               <p>The Deuil now assaulting the woman in the absence of her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, first asketh her this questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 1.</note>
                  <hi>Yea, hath God indeed said, Yee shall not eat of euery tree of the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den?</hi> Vnto whom she answered: <hi>Wee eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden. But of the fruit of the tree which is in the middes of the</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17903:15"/>
                  <hi>garden, God hath said, Yee shall not eat of it, neither touch it</hi> (and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in said more than we finde God did, for hee did not forbid tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching) <hi>lest peradventure yee dye</hi> (and therein said lesse) for God said, they should dye without any peradventure. The Deuill then, being like the serpent out of whom he spake, hauing thus got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in his head, and made the woman to hearken vnto him, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily brought in his whole bodie: for he had no sooner said, <hi>Yee shall not dye at all;</hi> when presently the woman was perswaded to eat, and being more forwardly with her husband, than the serpent was with her, gaue vnto him, and he did eat likewise. Although it seemeth very strange, that Adam resembling God in wisdome, did not rather reprooue his wife, than so rashly follow her exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And forasmuch as it may
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17903:16"/> seeme an vnreasonable matter to reasonable men, that God should be so much displeased for the eating of an apple, or such like: we are to know, that vnder this sinne, others also are cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. As first, infidelitie or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strust of Gods goodnesse: and we see, that a good meaning man taketh no iniurie so much to heart, as when such, whom hee hath done well for, haue a bad opinion of him, as though he were their enemie. Secondly, there was pride, in that not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with the estate wherein God had placed them, they would needs better it against his will. And were it onely a bare breach of Gods commandement, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either distrust or pride ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned thereunto: we know, that a subiect, especially of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner sort, were something to blame, if he durst pull an apple
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17903:16"/> in his Princes garden, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand forbidden so to doe. It was then a fault in Adam: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth not our owne reason now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>each vs, that by how much he is greater against whom an offence is committed, by so much the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is greater, and deserueth greater punishment? Gods greatnesse then being infinite, Adams fault was no lesse, our owne reason being iudge. Thus haue I laid before thine eyes the grieuousnesse of this sin: which I counsell thee alwaies to haue in minde. For I nothing doubt, but God by this their sin in the beginning, would haue vs learne euer after, how he estee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of euery sinne, be it but the eating of an apple against his commandement. For consider, it was not murther, it was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie, nor any such like; but onely the eating of an apple one
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17903:17"/> time: and yet by reason of Gods greatnesse this sinne deserued e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlasting damnation, according vnto reason it selfe, howsoeuer many not well considering the matter, doe thinke the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment for eating the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruit:</hi>
                  </note> God then being iustly displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with our first Parents, thrust them out of Paradise, lest eating of the tree of life they should liue euermore. For although, had the tree vertue to preserue mans life, God might haue bereaued it thereof at his pleasure: yet, if God gaue it for a signe vnto them, that whiles they did eat thereof, they should liue; eating thereof they must needs liue, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God is truth and cannot lye. That therefore they, and their posteritie (as taking substance from them) might now taste of death, not onely temporarie, but euerlasting too <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Except yee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>esh, &amp;c.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oh. 6. 53.</note> (excepting those alone, which since haue fed on
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17903:17"/> Christ) they were sent forth into this cursed earth: where, how many miseries both they and wee haue sustained, experience doth better teach, than I am able. Not to stand then vpon bodily cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, as pertaining nothing to our purpose, and which all of themselues doe easily perceiue: know, that euery mothers child may now say, as the Prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid doth, <note place="margin">Psal. 51.</note>
                  <hi>I was borne in iniquitie, and in sinne hath my mother concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me.</hi> So that by nature, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soone as we haue any being, wee are hatefull in the sight of God: euen as a young wolfe, or other harmefull beast, is in our eyes; whom wee doe hate, not for the hurt he hath already done; but because we know his nature to be such, that when he commeth to yeeres, he will doe harme, if oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion bee offered. Our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God and goodnesse is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17903:18"/> cleane gone, <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> for <hi>the naturall man perceiueth not the things of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God;</hi> yea, so foolish are wee and ignorant, <note place="margin">Psal. 73.</note> euen as beasts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. If we had knowledge to doe good, yet were there no will: if will, then wanted wee power; <note place="margin">Philip. 2.</note>
                  <hi>For it is God that worketh in vs, both the will and the deed, euen of his good pleasure.</hi> Nay, so far are we from knowing, or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or doing that which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth God, that of our selues wee cannot so much as thinke a good thought; for, <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3. Gen. 6. 5.</note>
                  <hi>all the imaginations</hi> (and not some onely) <hi>of thoughts of mans heart are wholly euill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually</hi> (and not onely for a time.) In a word, by nature we are no better than filthy styes (as it were) of that vncleane spirit the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: our wils being so wholly linked vnto his will, that hee no sooner biddeth vs goe, but wee goe; come, but we come; doe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17903:18"/> this, but as obedient seruants, or rather willing slaues, we are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to doe it out of hand. And in this miserable estate wee all continue, as vtterly vnable to helpe our selues; vntill it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth God of his free mercy in his sonne Christ the second Adam, to send downe his holy Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hearts, who driuing the vncleane Spirit out of his posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, taketh vp his lodging there, and regenerateth, or causeth vs to become new creatures. This God doth vnto some at one time and vnto others at another; as our Sauiour sheweth in the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell by Saint Matthew. <note place="margin">Mat. 20</note> There hee likeneth God to an house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, which goeth out at the dawning of the day to hire la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers into his vineyard: and againe, about the third, sixth, ninth, and eleuenth houre, which is the last houre in the day saue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17903:19"/> one. For the Iewes parted the time between sunne-rising and sunne-set into twelue parts, were the day longer or shorter: and when the sunne had been vp one part of the twelue, they called that, the first houre: and when it lacked but one part of going downe, they called that, the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth houre. The meaning now of this parable is, that God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth men effectually by his holy Spirit vnto amendment of life; some being very young, at the first houre of the day; others, at twenty, forty, threescore, yea fourescore yeeres of age, or vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; when the sunne beginneth to set, when their liues begin to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d, and they are ready to goe vnderground. But now, it shall suffice for our purpose to make two sorts onely; and to say, that God sanctifieth some, before they come to yeeres of discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17903:19"/> and others after they come to some age. Those, of whom the holy Ghost tooke possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he might <hi>dwell in them</hi> (as the Apostle speaketh) <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> before they come to yeeres of discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; can hardly know by the time before, or when hee tooke possession, that he is in the house. For being not past fourteene yeeres of age or thereabout, they had not discretion to marke any alteration in themselues: and moreouer, seeing they were not long accustomed to the vanities of the world, they found happily no great difficultie to leaue and forsake them. But these being (I thinke) few in number, may know it by the whole course of their liues since, of which I will speake anon. Those, in whose hearts the holy Ghost tooke vp his lodging after they came to some yeeres, may know by the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17903:20"/> manner of their liues before, by the manner of their liues when, and by the manner of their liues since hee entred, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter is there abiding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. Of the manner of our liues, before we become the Temple of the holy Ghost.</head>
               <p>BEfore the spirit of God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in a man, hee shall haue trouble of minde, and his consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will bee much disquieted. For the holy Ghost vseth the word of God (called by S. Paul, <hi>the sword of the Spirit</hi>) as a means to expell the vncleane Spirit out of his dwelling place. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The holy Ghosts weapon.</hi> Ephes. 6.</note> This sword of the Spirit hath edges on both sides: <note place="margin">Reuel. 1.</note> this word of God contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in it, both threatnings of death and damnation against the wicked, and promises of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17903:20"/> and saluation vnto those, which repent from the bottome of their hearts, and will not suffer the Deuill to haue either vpper or lower roome there any more. Now, when a sinner, be he an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressour, adulterer, drunkard, swearer, dicer, &amp;c. heareth and considereth Gods threatnings in his word against his sinnes, hee beginneth to feare his own estate, which feare is the beginning of true wisdome. I know well, there are many so obstinate, that heare they neuer so many threatnings, yet are nothing at all thereby made afraid: but I speake of him; vnto whom God being gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, meaneth to bestow on him the grace of his holy Spirit. Such a man (I say) hauing a guiltie conscience, feareth lest those plagues will befall him: but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering further the promises of God to the penitent, hee purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17903:21"/> with himselfe (being moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the holy Ghost) to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a new man: which assoone as the Deuill perceiueth, present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he beginneth to play his part, if by any meanes hee may keepe him still vnder his subiection: and then shall a mans minde be troubled, the Deuill tempting him to continue in his sins, and the holy Ghost moouing him to amend his former life. When a strong man armed keepeth his house, the house it selfe will be in quietnesse: but when a stronger commeth to driue him foorth, then will the house be much dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted and broken downe; the one striuing to breake in thorow the doore, window, or wall; and the other being ready to resist at all places. For howsoeuer the man within knoweth himselfe to bee the weaker, yet will hee not yeeld straightway, seeing he stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17903:21"/> on the surer ground, and hath the house on his side. In like manner, as long as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill (who is likened to a strong man) <note place="margin">Luk. 11.</note> keepeth our soules vnder his subiection, and ruleth vs at his pleasure; so long (it may be) we shall haue quietnesse of mind: but when the holy Ghost being stronger commeth to take pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of vs, then will our minds be much disquieted. For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer the Deuill be the weaker, yet will he not yeeld in haste, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing that we take his part: and being loth to let vs goe, hee will not spare the house, but will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist at all places, and vse his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to the vttermost.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Deuils weapons.</hi>
                  </note> The weapons of the Deuill are two: the one, Despaire: the other, Presumption. And he will vse both to euery man, if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; although he will happily vse one in greater measure than
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17903:22"/> the other. If a man be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon theefe, drunkard, swearer, whore-master, or any such no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious wicked liuer; and hearing out of Gods word that none such shall be saued, is earnestly moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the holy Ghost to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake his sinnes: then for the most part will the Deuill labour most to haue such a man despaire, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading him, that his sinnes are so horrible, his life so wicked, that God will not forgiue him. Thus hee serued Cain: <note place="margin">Genes. 4.</note> thus hee serued Iudas: &amp; thus (no doubt) he hath serued some other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides. If a man be no such noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious wicked liuer, but giuen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer much to the vaine vanities of the world, as dancing, carding, bowling, &amp;c. and hearing that he which is a friend of this world, is an enemie vnto God; <note place="margin">Iam. 4.</note> beginneth to withdraw his affection from these fooleries: then vsually will
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17903:22"/> the Deuill tempt such a man most to presume, assuring his conscience <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> (for the father of lies makes no conscience of a lie) that howsoeuer he walketh in the way to hel, and keepeth still the same path, yet Gods mercie is so great, as that hee shall come to heauen in the end. Thus hath the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill preuailed, I nothing doubt, with almost infinite thousands: yea, for one that Despaire hath kept vnder his subiection, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption (I am perswaded) hath kept many hundreds. But now, against these weapons of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill the holy Ghost will oppose the two edged sword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: and that a man should not despaire, will put him in minde of many comfortable sayings in Gods word; as, that at what time soeuer a sinner doth repent, &amp;c. that God willeth not the death of a sinner; that he delighteth in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17903:23"/> mercie; that he is the Father of mercies: in a word, that Gods mercie is infinite, and seeing his sinnes are not so, therefore Gods mercie is greater than his sinnes; which he also shall one day finde, if presently he will forsake them. Againe, that a man should not presume neither, the holy Ghost will lay before his eies some ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible examples of Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vpon sinners; as, vpon Saul, for sparing the Amalekites; <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15</note> vpon Adam, for eating an apple only: and also some fearfull say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; as, that God is a consuming fire; that the soule which sinneth, shall die; that wee shall giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of euery idle word, &amp;c. Thus then, the Deuill striuing to keepe our soules, and the holy Ghost striuing to driue him foorth; our soules and conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will be much disquieted, the house in the meane season will be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17903:23"/> broken downe. And to the end (gentle Reader) thou mightest make some triall heereof in thy selfe, before I goe any further: Art thou a drunkard, whore-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, profaner of the Lords day, a dicer, a carelesse Minister, a corrupt Magistrate? Or hast thou iniured any man by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, theft, coosening; or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest in any such sinne? And doth the holy Ghost mooue thee now (marke, whether he doth or not) for feare of Gods anger to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake this thy wickednesse? Let him then make a breach in the house; let him perswade thee to amend; doe thou purpose with thy selfe to forsake thy drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, whoredome, dicing, &amp;c. or if thou hast iniured any man, to make him some recompence. And then shalt thou see, what a stirre the Deuill will keepe in thy minde, before thou shalt bring it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17903:24"/> to passe, and shalt forsake, either thy whoredome, gaming, profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Lords day, &amp;c. or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store ill gotten goods. And now I pray thee, marke what I say. If the Deuill will so much disquiet thy minde, before hee will lose one roome in the house, and thou shalt forsake any one sinne; which hauing done, thou maist be his slaue still: what stirre (is it likely) he will keepe, before hee will lose all the roomes, and thou shalt forsake all thy sinnes; which hauing done, thou shalt become the Temple of the holy Ghost? I warrant thee, the Deuill will not so let thee goe: but will first much trouble thy minde, and suffer the house to bee broken downe. Thou knowest, when he was cast foorth of mens bodies, <note place="margin">Mark. 1.</note> how hee did vex and rent them: and will hee then be cast out of our soules and consciences with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17903:24"/> no adoe? No, thinke not so: if thou wilt goe to heauen, thou must saile by hell: if thou wilt haue the peace of God which passeth all vnderstanding, thou must be content to endure some trouble first at the Deuils hands. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Trouble of minde, in some more, in some lesse.</hi> Act <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> But this trouble (I know) is in some lesse, and of lesse continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; as it was in those, of whom we reade in the second of the Acts. For S. Peter had no soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner handled the sword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and they were only <hi>pricked in their hearts</hi> therewith; but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently three thousand were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Church, and became the Temple of Gods Spirit. In some againe, it is more, and of longer continuance; as it was in S. Augustine: who setting downe at large the strange combat that he felt in himselfe, yet writeth no more (I nothing doubt) than what some other doe likewise
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17903:25"/> know by experience. Now, the reason of this difference between men in this case, is very plaine and euident. For suppose, that a Christian Prince should with his armie breake into the Turkes dominion: would not the Turke fortifie those castles best, out of which being wonne, the enemie might doe him most harme? So, whom the Deuill seeth to be the likeliest instruments for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of his kingdome, if once they are become the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the holy Ghost; those is he most loth to let goe out of his subiection, those doth he fortifie most against all good inspirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and neuer giue ouer, vntill he see the castle beaten flat to the ground. Examine now thy selfe (gentle Reader) whether thy minde at any time heeretofore hath beene troubled for thy sins, or whether thou hast alwaies li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17903:25"/> at one stay and in quietnesse. If thou hast, it is the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous: for, before possession be gotten, the house must needs be something battered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. Of the manner of our liues, when we become the Temple of the holy Ghost.</head>
               <p>WHEN the holy Ghost hath entred, and a man is truly sanctified: then, after this storme, there will follow a calme. For thou knowest, that if a strong man be once driuen out of his house by one that is stron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the house shall not be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken downe any more: and when the holy Ghost hath driuen the wicked Spirit cleane out of his possession, a man shal haue peace and quietnesse of minde. For then indeed shall he be willing to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17903:26"/> forsake his sins; and moreouer, shall haue faith in God, which it is not possible hee should haue, the Deuill bearing rule. For it is the Spirit of God onely, which can truly assure our spirits, <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> that wee are the children of God. Which assurance vntill we haue, we can no more put our trust or haue faith in God, than wee can put our trust in the greatest ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies we haue, and looke for any fauour at their hands.</p>
               <p>This now is the time, when a man is said to be borne againe: <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oh. 3.</note>
                  <hi>Except a man bee borne</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> And indeed, some shall feele such a change, that they shall thinke themselues euen borne againe; yea, new men, and almost in another world. I doe not say, that all shall: but if this alteration were small in any,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17903:26"/> Christ would not (I thinke) haue said, <hi>Except a man be borne,</hi> &amp;c. hee would rather haue giuen it some other word. Surely, it is a very strange matter to be borne againe: but yet (in my opinion) it were more strange, for a man to be borne againe after he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to yeeres of discretion, and not to take notice thereof euer after. This againe is the time, when a man shall first know; that God is light, <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.</note> and in him is no darknesse. For some (whether few, or many, I cannot say) shall euen sensibly perceiue a light then shining into their hearts and consciences. And of this time it is, that Christ speaketh in the fifteenth of Saint Luke: <note place="margin">Luk. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for assoone as the holy Ghost ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth possession of vs, hee giueth vs faith, whereupon immediately followeth repentance. Christs words in S. Luke are: <hi>There is</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:17903:27"/>
                  <hi>more ioy in heauen ouer one sinner that repenteth, than there is ouer ninety and nine iust persons, that need no repentance.</hi> It is a true saying, as comming from him which is truth it selfe: and I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubt, but many know this to be true also; <hi>There is more ioy in one sinner when he repenteth, than there is in ninety and nine iust per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, which haue repented long agoe.</hi> Oh (deare brother) consider with thy selfe, if thou laiest in prison fast bound, being condemned to a cruell death; and suddenly one should bring thee word, that in stead of the expected torment, thou shouldest haue an vnexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted kingdome, for thy Prince had chosen thee for his heire: How welcome would that ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings be vnto thee? How would it comfort thy troubled spirit? Couldest thou almost containe that sudden ioy? Let it not then
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17903:27"/> seeme strange, if that mans ioy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e then wonderfull, when the holy Ghost shall bring his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science word; that whereas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he was ready to be cast into hell fire (which then he shal both know, and also well consider) he is now become the child of God, hauing all the godly for his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and Christ himselfe for his elder brother, with whom he is fellow-heire of the kingdome of heauen. The consideration of this his estate will greatly reioice him euer after; but yet, at that time most, when first the holy Ghost sealeth it in his heart and conscience. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The holy Ghosts house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warming</hi>
                  </note> Surely, when the holy Ghost first taketh possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his manner is to keepe house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warming for a time.</p>
               <p>Examine now thy selfe (gentle Reader) whether thy minde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing troubled for thy sins heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, it was afterwards quiet; or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17903:28"/> not. If not; then know, that pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session was not gotten: for the holy Ghost would haue assured thy conscience of remission of thy sinnes, and then would not thy minde any longer be so trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for them. If thy minde was quiet afterwards, then consider the manner of thy life since, lest otherwise thou shouldest hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily be deceiued. For it may be, that thou hast had trouble of minde, and quietnesse after, and yet possession not gotten; as I will make plaine vnto thee by the former similitude. When one strong man striuing to driue another forth of his house, hath assaied to breake thorow the doore, wall, or window: and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth, that not onely the man within, but the house also, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the strong building, doth resist him, and put him to very much labour: It may be, when
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17903:28"/> he hath tried sometime, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill vtterly giue ouer, as iudging it not worth his paines; and then the house will be at quietnesse againe, and not broken downe any more. In like sort, when the holy Ghost commeth to driue the Deuill out from ruling vs; and perceiueth, that not only the Deuill, but wee also taking part with the Deuill, doe very much resist his good inspirations: It may be, that he will iudge vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie of his gouernment; and being offended (as one that sought our good, and not his owne) will after some assaults leaue troubling vs; and going his way, giue vs ouer wholly to the Deuill againe. Yea, consider with thy selfe (gentle Reader) whether thy minde hath not heeretofore beene disquieted, when thou hast heard at a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or read in some good
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17903:29"/> booke, Gods threatnings against thy sinnes. Nay, is not thy mind now troubled with feare? And yet, as heeretofore, so when thou hast left reading, thou shalt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily haue quietnesse, and posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion not taken neuerthelesse. For the holy Ghost seeing thee to take part with the Deuill (beware of it therefore) will happily goe his way, iudging thee vnworthie of his spirituall regiment: and then shalt thou haue quietnesse of minde, as thou haddest, before thou tookest my booke in hand. <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oh. 5.</note> A man then may haue quietnesse after trouble, and yet the house not wonne: hee may also haue some kinde of reioicing, and yet the Comforter not there abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. That thou maist not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be deceiued, consider the whole course of thy life since that time: for a new master will not lightly order his house, as he
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17903:29"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d that was in it before. And howsoeuer some (as I haue said heeretofore) cannot know by the manner of their liues before, or when, the holy Ghost tooke pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session, that hee is in the house: yet by the manner of their liues now (were they sanctified in their mothers wombe, as Iohn Baptist was) <note place="margin">Luk. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> euery one may know, who is housholder. For the holy Ghost will not gouerne vs, as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill would, they are of so contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie a nature. Marke well then this that followeth: and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that I speake not of the strong Christian; only I say this vnto him, Let him that standeth, take heed lest he fall: but of the weake Christian, who being the Temple of the holy Ghost, and hauing indeed a sauing faith, is sometimes much in doubt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and of the carelesse and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuous Christian, who being
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17903:30"/> a slaue of the Deuill, and hauing no true faith at all, yet doth not perceaue his lamentable estate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. Of the manner of our liues, after we are become the Temple of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghost: and first, of his testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony vnto our soules and consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</head>
               <p>IF thou art in the state of salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and hast truely repented: if thou art the child of God, and hast a true sauing faith: if (which commeth all to one) the holy Ghost dwelleth in thee, then hath hee heretofore made knowen to the house who is housholder, and doth still some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times assure thy conscience, that thou art the childe of God; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of S. Paul to the Romans, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</note>
                  <hi>The same spirit</hi> (<hi>which dwelleth in vs,</hi> verse 11.) <hi>beareth</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17903:30"/>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>nesse to our spirit, that we are the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ildren of God.</hi> But now, seeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e Deuill also falsly perswadeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e wicked, that they are regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and shall be saued: how should a man know, whether this perswasion or assurance com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the holy Ghost, or from that wicked and deceauing spirit? I will shew thee how, God assisting me with his holy Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the assurance.</hi>
                  </note> First, if the holy Ghost dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in thee, then will hee open thine eyes to see thy sinnes, not onely outward, but inward also; and moreouer, will cause thee to esteeme euery sinne (be it neuer so little in other mens sight) a great offence against God. For this serueth to the setting forth of the glory of Gods grace and mercy, which appeareth to be by so much the greater, by how much his sins are more hainous, whom God forgiueth: and we see,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17903:31"/> how S. Paul doth magnifie the mercy of God, <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.</note> in that when hee was a blasphemer and persecuter of the Church, he was notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing receiued to fauour. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, this serueth to the encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of our loue towards God: for hee to whom much is forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, will loue much; whereof we haue an example in the sinner, of whom our Sauiour testified, saying: <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uk. 7.</note>
                  <hi>Many sinnes are forgiuen hir, for shee loued much.</hi> But now, though a man see his sinnes, and duly esteemeth them, yet will the holy Ghost assure his conscience of pardon, drawing his argument from the mercy of God: for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, though we haue heretofore and daily doe many waies offend God, yet his mercy is greater then our sins, and for his sonnes sake hee will be mercifull to his children.</p>
               <p>Contrariwise, if the Deuill
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17903:31"/> dwelleth in thee, hee will not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> thee to see some sinnes, as thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nt of faith, thy inward pride, malice, couetousnesse, selfe-loue &amp;c. and those outward sins which thou seest, as thy mocking, foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h iesting, lying, swearing, coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sening, drunkennesse, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome &amp;c. hee will cause thee to esteeme small offences. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as then the holy Ghost ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his testimony and assurance on the infinite mercy of God, the Deuill contrariwise on the smalnesse of our sins. And what shall we heare some say; I am no common lyer, swearer, drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard &amp;c. and though I sometime lie, sweare, pilfer, deceaue, be drunken &amp;c. yet this is no great matter, God will easily pardon this, and I see al men liue as bad; wherefore I shall be saued as well as they.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> continuall</hi>
                  </note> Secondly, if this perswasion
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17903:32"/> commeth from the holy Ghost, then is it not continuall; nay, in some very seldome: whereas their doubtings whether they shall be saued, are very often, and almost euery day. For (marke it well) if a man hath some assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from Gods spirit, that he is the childe of God, and fellow heire with Iesus Christ of the kingdome of heauen: then shall he with Saint Paul account this world and worldly things as vile in comparison thereof, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that of our Sauior Christ, <note place="margin">Math. 13. 44.</note>
                  <hi>The kingdome of heauen is like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a treasure hid in the field, which when a man hath found, he hideth it, and for ioy thereof departeth, and selleth all</hi> (not a part only) <hi>that he hath and buieth that field.</hi> The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God then, and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in his sonne Christ, being a mans chiefest treasure, where that is, there will his heart be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17903:32"/> and seeing his assurance is b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> small (as no mans, I thinke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> these daies is great at the first) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> chiefest care shall be, how he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ay be certain and out of doubt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>st happily in the end he should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nde himselfe deceiued. If a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orldly minded man were in some hope of obtayning a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome here on earth, how would hee beat his braines thereabout continually, casting this way and that way with himselfe, and neuer be quiet in minde day nor night, vntill he were sure of obtayning his desired promotion; yea, and though he were neuer so sure, yet would scarse thinke himselfe sure enough, vntil he were in full pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session thereof? Indeed, it is most true as our Sauiour saith, <note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> that <hi>the children of this world are in their generation wiser then the children of light:</hi> and therfore a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian will not be so carefull of his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17903:33"/> future estate, as a worldling of the present. But yet, I leaue it to thy consideration, whether the childe of light is not more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of comming to heauen, then he himselfe would be of obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning some earthly promotion; although not so carefull happily as a child of this world would be in the like case. A weake Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians minde then running chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on these matters, although at sometimes hee be in good hope, and thinketh that he euer stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on sure ground: yet at other times happily it will be otherwise with him, and he shall haue these or the like cogitations. I know, that I haue many waies grieuous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offended God; and howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he hath promised to forgiue al those which beleeue in Christ: yet, how doe I know, that he will forgiue me? How doe I know, that I doe truely beleeue? <note place="margin">Luk. 18.</note> Few
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17903:33"/> men (saith our Sauiour) hath a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e faith: few men, I often heare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>de the straight gate: how doe I know certainly, that I am one of those few? I doe not see it writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Scriptures, that God hath chosen me by name. And then, considering his owne infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, together with the want of Gods graces, his minde shall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times be much troubled with doubting.</p>
               <p>True it is, as before I haue said, that when the holy Ghost first taketh possession, there will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low peace and quietnesse: but yet this quietnesse in some continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth very short time. For the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill being in a rage that he is cast forth, will striue to come in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and seeke by all meanes to disquiet vs: so that, what through his temptatiōs, what through our own corrupt nature, we shal often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times much doubt, and some at
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17903:34"/> sometimes euen almost despaire of their saluation. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a weake Christian and one that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paireth.</hi>
                  </note> If here it be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: Seeing the Deuill tempteth some to despaire before the house is won, and others after; how should I know of whether sort I am? Ans: Euen by this: if the vnclean spirit be not yet cast forth, then dost thou nourish (as it were) such temptations: and howsoeuer thou knowest thy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable estate, yet dost thou not call vpon God; as Iudas did not, for ought we finde: or if thou dost with thy lips, yet canst thou not for thy life pray heartily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that he would haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vpon thee. Whereas, if the holy Ghost hath gotten possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then commonly disliking thy selfe for distrusting Gods goodnesse; faine wouldest thou beleeue, faine wouldest thou haue Gods graces as plentifully as any man, and so (to vse the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17903:34"/> words of our Sauiour Christ) <note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> euen hunger and thirst after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>teousnesse. Diddest thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> (gentle Reader) after long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ing euen long for the food <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy bodie? Such a longing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>alt thou, feeling the want of Gods graces, the spirituall food of thy soule, haue after them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so: and therefore, seeing euery good gift commeth downe from aboue, <note place="margin">Iam. 1.</note> shalt heartily and earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call vpon thy heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; who meaning in some good measure to satisfie thee at length, will it may be defer the time very long, as it shall seem to thee, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Wherefore God defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of his graces.</hi>
                  </note> that so thou maiest esteeme his graces the more, and be more thankfull vnto him, when he hath granted thy request.</p>
               <p>Contrariwise, if this perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on commeth from the lying Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, then is it alwaies the same: and such a man thinketh, that hee
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17903:35"/> hath a strong faith, whensoeuer hee thinketh vpon this matter; which indeed he doth very sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as hauing small care of his owne estate. But if vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion it commeth into his minde, then commonly he hath these or the like cogitations. I know, I am a sinner: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Thus I haue heard some speak.</hi>
                  </note> but God is mercifull, God is merciful; what need I trouble my selfe about these matters? The Preacher saith, I must beleeue stedfastly, and so I will. Hereupon, he stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to put these thoughts quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of his minde, and is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded, that hee hath alwaies a strong faith, whereas it is onely a blind presumption. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a strong Christian, and one that presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth.</hi>
                  </note> If heere now it be asked: Seeing he that hath a strong faith, is alwaies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded, that he hath such a one; how should a man know, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath a strong faith, or a strong and blind presumption?
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17903:35"/> Ans: Very easily. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Few I think haue a strong faith in these daies.</hi>
                  </note> First, he that ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> a strong faith, is euen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>st as certaine of his saluation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f he were in heauen already. Whereas he that blindly presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>th, if he would enter into his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ne heart well, should easily perceiue, that he greatly doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>th of his saluation. Secondly, the strong Christian hath some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time (I thinke) been something troubled with doubting of Gods fauour, and knoweth himselfe to bee now more assured thereof, than he was heretofore. Hast not thou (gentle Reader) since thou wast a young child, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thy selfe to grow &amp; increase in strength? Thus it fareth with a man, after he is borne againe, and become the child of God: he receiueth <hi>grace vpon grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> and goeth from strength, to strength, and may (if he marke it) perceiue how he groweth vp <note place="margin">Ephes. 4.</note>
                  <hi>vnto a perfect</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:17903:36"/>
                  <hi>man, vnto the measure of the age <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the fulnesse of Christ.</hi> Whereas the presumptuous Christian knoweth not what a weake faith meaneth; he neuer perceiued hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faith to increase: but fondly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swadeth himselfe, that he hath now a strong faith, and euer had. Thirdly, a strong faith at all times greatly comforteth a man, farre more than if some Prince had chosen him to be his heyre: for he knoweth himselfe heyre of the kingdome of heauen. And, what through the cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his saluation, what through the hatred of his owne sinnes, he shall vnfainedly say with Saint Paul, <note place="margin">Philip. 1.</note>
                  <hi>I desire to be loosed, and to be with Christ.</hi> Yea, sometimes I thinke he shall haue such a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging after death, as that he can scarse be content to liue any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, were it in neuer so great worldly prosperitie. Whereas,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17903:36"/> let him that hath a strong pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ption, consider; whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> assurance of eternall life doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oyce him asmuch, as the assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ce of an earthly kingdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ld: let him examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lfe, whether he would not giue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>is hope of heauen heereafter, for a Lord-ship out of hand, so that he might be sure to dye as other creatures doe, and neuer come to iudgment. As for death, hee hath small longing after it, vnlesse it be for the miseries, wherein he liueth: it is not for the certaintie of his saluation; much lesse is it for the hatred of his sinnes, because by them he offendeth God, which hath been to him a louing father.</p>
               <p>Examine now thy selfe by that which hath been said: for if thou readest on still without pausing, one matter will bring another out of thy head, and so it will do
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17903:37"/> thee no good. It is God, which mooueth thee to read; but it is the Deuill, which tempteth thee lightly to passe it ouer: and if he can now keepe thee from exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thy selfe, he will doe it with greater ease heereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. Of the holy Ghosts ordering that mans life, in whom he dwelleth.</head>
               <p>BEsides the testimonie of Gods Spirit vnto our soules and consciences, there is yet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther marke, whereby a man may know, whether the holy Ghost dwelleth in him, or not: and that is, his behauiour to God and his neighbour. For a good tree may bee knowen by his good fruit: and a good faith sheweth it selfe by good actions. A wise house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder will order his house wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and if the holy Ghost dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17903:37"/> in vs, we shall be ordered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ordingly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most roome kept most cleane.</hi>
                  </note> Now, to the well ordering of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> house, one thing required, is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat the outward roomes be not onely well gouerned, but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most most especially, where the Master is most conversant. And if the holy Ghost be the Master, then shall we not onely doe that which is good outwardly, as giue almes, pray, heare or read Gods word, and the like: but we shall doe it well also, euen with a good minde and heartily; as seeking to please God, who is delighted with adverbes, and liketh not bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. i. good, vnlesse it be <hi>benè.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> well too. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Some keepe all the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward rooms cleane.</hi>
                  </note> There are some which liue outwardly as well as the best, and are liberall, no swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, frequent Sermons, &amp;c. for the holy Ghost hath wonne all the outward roomes, and driuen the Deuill to the inmost, to the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17903:38"/> castle, to the heart; where he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring rule, marreth all. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee cannot hinder them from giuing almes: yet hee can make them do it with a minde to be praised, as hypocrites did. <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he cannot cause them to murther the innocent: yet hee can make them to abstaine onely for feare, as the Scribes did. <note place="margin">Luk. 20.</note> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he cannot hinder them from preaching and teaching Gods word: yet hee can make them doe it with an intent to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure talents to themselues, and not to Christ, as some false A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles did in S. Pauls time. <note place="margin">Philip. 3.</note> Whereas, if the holy Ghost ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that roome, the heart, will be kept most cleane, as being the chiefest place of his abode: (although indeed, neither this, nor the rest, so cleane, but that there needeth continuall clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing; for howsoeuer the vncleane
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17903:38"/> Spirit be cast forth, yet leaueth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> such a bad sauour behind him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>at it can neuer be done away, whiles we haue our being heere.) Was not the Temple all ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid with gold on the inside, <note place="margin">1. King. 6.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though on the outside it was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with lead, tile, or the like? Marke then what I say, and God giue thee vnderstanding in all things. If thou be the Temple of God, if the holy Ghost dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in thee, thou art all ouerlaid with gold within: though the whole Temple be holy, yet the inmost roome is the holy of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes, or most holy: thy hart goeth beyond thy hand, foote, eye, &amp;c. so that (like vnto S. Paul) <note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> thou canst not doe so much good, nor so sincerely as thou wouldest. Wherefore thou wilt dislike thy best actions, perceiuing thine owne imperfections: and being sorry for them, wilt call vpon
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17903:39"/> God for more grace, that so thou maiest be able to amend. If thou bee not guided by the holy Ghost, then doest thou more good than thou wouldest: for when thou doest any, it is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause thou wouldest doe good; but either for feare, or hope of reward, otherwise thou wouldest not haue done it. And againe, thou art sorry because enough others do not perceiue thy good deeds; and wouldest faine haue them counted better than they are.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>All the roomes, &amp; at all times, shalbe well ordered.</hi>
                  </note> Another point of a wise hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder is to see, that not some onely, or at some times; but that all the roomes at all times be wel ordered. And if the holy Ghost be housholder, hee will haue a care, that the whole house shall alwayes be ordered according to Gods will and pleasure. The hands and feet shal labour hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stly
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17903:39"/> for their liuing: and if they haue stollen any thing at any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>me before, shal now be ready to goe and restore it againe. The eyes and eares, in steed of loue-bookes, playes, and such like; shall be busie in reading and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and the tongue in talking, of Gods word. The mind (marke it well) shall haue litle leisure to examine other mens liues, for looking to his owne wayes, and considering, whether the hands, eyes, eares, and all the parts of the bodie, bee alwaies obedient vnto God or not. Were the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost a soiourner onely, hee would happily looke but to some three or foure roomes, and for three or foure moneths, or thereabout. But now, hee is said <hi>to dwell in vs;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3</note> and therefore will looke that all the roomes bee at all times well ordered, in respect of those businesses, about which
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17903:40"/> they are imployed. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Some keepe all the roomes cleane at some times.</hi>
                  </note> There are many now a dayes, which haue certaine times of seruing God: and then they make a great shew of religion, so that neither right eye nor right hand are spared; but the one is pulled out, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cut off, and both cast away, as though they should neuer bee fetched againe. S. Augustine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth of his time, that it was then a common custome to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre their Baptisme vntil twenty yeeres of age, or vpward: and the reason was, that so in the meane space they might liue like Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and more licentiously. Hereupon came this prouerbe: <hi>Let him alone, he may doe what he will, he is not yet baptised.</hi> And is not the like now happened in the other Sacrament? So that this may now bee a prouerbe: <hi>Let him alone, he may doe what he will, hee meaneth not yet to receiue the</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:17903:40"/>
                  <hi>Communion.</hi> This sort of men, nough they liue like Pagans all the yeere, yet they vsually coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfet great holinesse at Easter: so that a man would halfe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, the vncleane Spirit to bee cleane gone out of them. <note place="margin">Luk. 11.</note> But within a while after, we may see him returned, &amp; to haue brought seuen Spirits worse than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe; for they commonly liue worse than they did before: the right eye and the right hand are fetched againe in the Deuils name. Of all kind of men their state seemeth most desperate: for if they dye at any other time of the yeere, there is litle or no hope of saluation. And though they haue so good hap as to dye at Easter, yet seeing man is not iudge, who looketh vpon the outward appearance onely for the time present; but God, <note place="margin">1. Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> who is a searcher of the heart and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17903:41"/> reynes, and knoweth whether they meane with the sowe that is washed, to wallow againe in the mire; I stand in great doubt of them, least happily they should not speed well then neither.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Others keep some rooms cleane at all times.</hi>
                  </note> Others there are, which are content to keepe some roomes cleane at all times: they are like vnto Herod; who heard Iohn gladly, and reformed many things: but one thing was lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, he would not leaue his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wife. <note place="margin">Mark. 6.</note> And so, they do not, neither would leaue all their sins: but thinke within themselues, as Naaman sometime said; <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. King. 5.</note>
                  <hi>The Lord be mercifull to vs in this.</hi> This is our right eye: this is our right hand: should wee pull out our right eye, and cut off our right hand, and cast them from vs? The Lord bee mercifull to vs in this. But the Lord will not bee mercifull vnto them: for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>souer
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17903:41"/> the holy Ghost hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n all the other outward rooms, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t the Deuill lyeth at the heart, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd sheweth himselfe through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>is. As indeed it shall escape him hardly, but lest hee should be stifled, hee will haue one out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward roome to take the aire, one roome whereout he may breath his venome: wherby those which haue the gift of discerning spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, may soone perceiue what Spirit ruleth within. If the holy Ghost had once gotten the hart, the strongest roome, hee would soone driue the Deuill out of all.</p>
               <p>Indeed, it often commeth to passe, that howsoeuer the Deuill hath lost all the roomes, yet he afterward stealeth into some of them againe. For, suppose that a strong man bee driuen forth of his house by one that is stron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: yet when he perceiueth the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17903:42"/> other to haue gone into some in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward roome, hee may breake in through the doore or window (the house of it selfe being not strong inough) and order the next roome, as hee seeth good. So, howsoeuer the Deuill were wholly cast forth, yet when hee perceiueth, that the holy Ghost being <hi>grieued</hi> by vs, <note place="margin">Ephes. 4.</note> is gone into the inmost roome; and hauing left vs to our selues, lyeth hid at the heart: hee may easily breake thorow the window or doore, &amp; dispose of the next roome at his pleasure. <note place="margin">2. Sam. 11</note> Thus he brake through Dauids windowes, that is, his eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liddes (Eccles: 12.) and hauing gotten the rule of his eyes, made him looke on a woman, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon hee committed adulterie. <note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> Thus hee brake through Peters doore, that is, his lippes (Eccles: 12.) and hauing gotten the rule of his tongue, in one night made
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17903:42"/> him three times to denie his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er. And thus it may befall any man: but yet, marke the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the godly and the wicked in this matter. A wicked man goeth with a full intent to sinne, and vpon premeditation; <note place="margin">2. Sam. 13</note> as Absalom did: who hauing conceiued mischiefe a long time, after two yeeres brought forth iniquitie, and slew his owne brother. Secondly, a wicked man after the deed done, feareth man more than God; as Saul did: who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired Samuel to honour him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Elders of his people, <note place="margin">1. Sam. 1</note> lest they following his example, should dishonour him, as he had dishonoured God in not destroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the king of Amalek. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a wicked man, if he escape vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punished, is more emboldened to doe the like; as Absalom was: who hauing taken away his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17903:43"/> life, and the law being not executed on him for it; thought afterward to haue bereaued his father, who neuer wronged him, both of life and kingdome too. <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15</note> Contrariwise, a godly man fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth at first into sinne vpon a sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den occasion, as Dauid and Peter did. <note place="margin">2. Sam. 11</note> For the one walking vpon the roofe of his house, saw a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man washing her selfe: and (as it seemeth) before he did either eat or sleepe, sent for her, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted adulterie. The other fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed after his master into the hall of the high Priest; <note place="margin">Matt. 26.</note> and when a question vnlooked for was as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked on the sudden, hee denied him, saying, <hi>I know not the man.</hi> Secondly, a godly man after an offense committed, feareth Gods anger more than mans; and therefore when he commeth to himselfe againe, will speedily runne to God for mercie, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sal. 51.</note> as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:17903:43"/> did; and Peter likewise, who w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t foorth and wept bitterly. Thirdly, a godly man will looke better to his owne waies, after he hath wholly recouered himselfe; Isay, after he hath wholly reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered himselfe. For the Deuill lightly will not be gone straight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and when he is gotten into one roome (beware therefore at the first) <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marke this, yee that feare God.</hi>
                  </note> hee may soone breake into the next, as being onely a thinne tearing, or some weake partition betweene them. Surely, if Peter hath once denied his master, he shall forsweare him in the end: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>A fearfull thing to consider.</hi>
                  </note> if Dauid hath lien with the wife, he shall murder the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and vpon premeditation too. But when the vncleane Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is cleane gone againe, then shall a man be more circumspect a good whiles after. Suppose, that a theefe had broken into thy house this last night: wouldest
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:17903:44"/> not thou bee more carefull in looking to all places; but most especially that, where the theefe brake in? So wil the holy Ghost. If the Deuill hath brought the fire of concupiscence into Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids eies; that roome shall bee well watered, his troubled spirit shall send foorth abundance of teares, which may keepe the fire from entring there any more. If Peters tongue hath for one night denied his master; it shall after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward day and night bee so farre from denying before priuate men, as that it shall confesse him boldly euen before the chiefe Priest himselfe; <note place="margin">Act. 4. 10.</note> and (no doubt) shall keepe others from doing the like, according to that charge of our Sauiour Christ, <note place="margin">Luk. 22.</note>
                  <hi>When thou art conuerted, strengthen thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> Indeed, it may be, that a godly man may fal into the same sinnes againe: the Deuill may
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17903:44"/> brake in at the same place again, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> also get many other outward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>omes, and keepe them long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>me: but yet at last, although <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ith some strife, hee shall againe be driuen foorth. For if the holy Ghost draue him out of his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, much more can he, and will he, out of any other hold: and alwaies after his departure grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter care shal be had to keepe him from entring either at those or any other places. Thus, euery thing, yea their sinnes also, shall turne for the best vnto those which feare God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Of the dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ference be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tweene t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> godly and wicked in praier.</hi>
                  </note> Thou seest now (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) that thou maist perceiue who is housholder, by the whole ordering of the house; and maist know, if thou bee the childe of God, by thy whole behauiour to thy father and brethren: but yet there are (I thinke) two particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars chiefly to be noted. One is
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:17903:45"/> Praier. For whereas a wicked mans praiers are alwaies about one stay, very cold; and if he be at any time more earnest than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is in words onely when some are present; or else, because of the miseries wherein hee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth: A godly man, as at other times he feeleth great alteration in himselfe, so doth he likewise in his praiers; sometime they are cold, sometime againe very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest; but yet commonly more earnest, when he praieth by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, than in companie; when he asketh forgiuenesse of his sinnes, than release of any worldly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serie. <hi>The holy Ghost</hi> (saith Paul) <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note>
                  <hi>maketh requests for vs</hi> (that is, stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs vp to pray) <hi>with sighes, which cannot be expressed.</hi> If then thou sometime, although sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, feelest these in thy praiers; seeing they come from the heart, thou maist <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ow who ruleth
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17903:45"/> there. How earnestly hast thou seene a prisoner begging for his life before an earthly Iudge? For him thus to doe, it was of nature: but it is a sure token of grace in thee, if thou canst thus earnestly call vpon thy heauenly Iudge for remission of thy sinnes, and the life eternall. Remember, that Gods house is the house of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. In the Temple sacrifices were daily offered: againe, the law was read and expounded. Yet, not the house of offering sacrifice; not the house of expounding or hearing the law: but <note place="margin">Esay 56.</note>
                  <hi>My house</hi> (saith God) <hi>shall bee called the house of praier for all nations.</hi> Of praier, I say; not, of much bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and lip-labour. The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles vsed much babling, <note place="margin">Matt. 6.</note> and thought to bee heard for the same. <note place="margin">Luk 20.</note> The Scribes vnder a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of long praying deuoured Widowes houses heeretofore.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:17903:46"/> The popish Priests and Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries going beyond them, vnder a pretence of long praying, through their much babling de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure Gentlemens houses in these daies. But Gods house is the house of true praier, which consisteth <hi>plus affectu quàm affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, gemitibus quàm verbis;</hi> not so much in words, as in sighes and grones fetched from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the heart.</p>
               <p>The other particular chiefly to be noted, is, our louing and peaceable carriage towards our brethren. Not Dauid a man of warre; but Salomon a Prince of peace must build God an house. <note place="margin">1. Chron. 22.</note> And wee reade in the Gospell by Saint Iohn, that when Iesus had said to his Disciples, <note place="margin">Ioh. 20.</note>
                  <hi>Peace bee vnto you:</hi> hee breathed on them, saying, <hi>Receiue ye the holy Ghost,</hi> as which should breed and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this peace among them.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17903:46"/> Surely, the holy Ghost gaue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s gifts to diuers men; <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12</note>
                  <hi>to one, the word of wisdome; to another, the word of knowledge; to another, faith; to another, the gifts of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> and the like. But yet, what saith S. Luke in the Acts? <note place="margin">Act. 4.</note>
                  <hi>The multitude of them that beleeued were of one heart and of one soule.</hi> Though the holy Ghost be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed sundry gifts vpon sundry men, yet hee gaue but one heart vnto al Christs Disciples. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I doe not maruell though Christ saith; <note place="margin">Ioh. 13.</note>
                  <hi>By this shall all men know that ye are my Disciples, if ye haue loue one to another.</hi> It may be some thinke, that Christ a little forgat himselfe: What, shall I not bee knowen to bee Christs Disciple by my often preaching or hearing of Gods word, by my much fasting, long praying, and the like? But heereby (saith Christ) shall men know you to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:17903:47"/> be my Disciples, if ye loue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For indeed, <hi>Hee that hath not the Spirit of Christ, is none of his:</hi> and if we haue Christs Spirit abiding in vs, it will assuredly giue one heart vnto vs all, to loue like brethren, and to liue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in vnitie. By thy praier to thy heauenly father, thou maist know: by thy loue to thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, both thy selfe and others may know, whether Christs Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit dwelleth in thee, or not. Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine now thy selfe by that which hath beene said. It may bee, if thou were asked, that thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest say: I see mine inward cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, I hunger after Gods graces, I am willing to forsake all my sinnes, my praier is feruent, my loue great, and the like. But enter into thine own heart (man) and make diligent search there, whether it be so indeed, or not: for I goe not about to teach thee
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:17903:47"/> how thou maist deceiue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but onely, how thou thy selfe maist not bee deceiued by thy selfe. And this know for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that a weake Christian meeting with such matters as these, will thorowly examine his owne estate, and rather bee too suspicious of it than otherwise: as for a carelesse Christian, hee hath small care of himselfe, and therefore will lightly passe it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, flattering himselfe in his owne carelesnesse. This is one marke more, wherby thou maist triethy selfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. A consolation to the weake Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, remouing the causes of his distrustfulnesse.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>A consola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> weake Christian</hi> Esay 42</note> TO the weake Christian this I say: and God grant, that such a one may know, that I
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:17903:48"/> speake to him. Thou art weake, but thou shalt be strengthned: thou art bruised, but thou shalt not be broken: thy Sauiour is not a destroier: he wil not breake the bruised reed, nor quench the smoking flax. Thou (poore soule) art often troubled with feare touching thine estate: thou doubtest, yea happily euen des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairest of Gods mercy: and sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vnlesse a man hath sometime heretofore beene somwhat trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with feare and doubting; I should greatly feare, I should ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much doubt, least that man were not in the state of saluation. Consider (good brother) consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the Deuill is thine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersary, a professed enemy to the child of God: hee chafeth, hee fretteth and fumeth, that his net is broken, and thou art deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: faine would hee hereafter, but seeing he shal not, now wil he
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:17903:48"/> disquiet thee. Remember, that he was a lyer from the beginning, and so wil shew himselfe vnto the end: whom he seeth out of Gods fauour, whom he knoweth to be his slaues, and ready to be cast in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell fire; those doth he falsly perswade, that they are out of all danger, and neuer suffer them so much as to perceiue their lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table estate: but whom he seeth God doth fauour, whom hee knoweth to be Christs brethren, and fellow-heires of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen; those will hee tempt very often to feare, to doubt, yea sometimes euen to despaire of their saluation. This assure thy selfe, that the holy Ghost neuer goeth about to haue a man despaire: he it is, which openeth our eyes to see our sins, that so we might learne to amend: but it is the Deuill which hereupon taketh occasion
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:17903:49"/> to tempt vs to distrust Gods goodnesse. And therefore take heed, that thou resistest him; do not nourish thy doubtings, but labour to ouercome them: and know, that whom the Deuil tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pteth to doubt, it is because hee doubteth of him; whom hee would haue despaire, it is because hee himselfe euen despaireth to haue him vnder his custody. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, he hath this way preuailed with some: but they haue beene few in comparison. No, no (deere brother) it is a dangerous case for him, when a man perceiueth his owne danger: whom he leadeth, hee must lead blindfolded, that they may be in hell, before they know whether they were going: hee well knoweth, that for one which despaireth of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, many hundreths presuming of Gods mercy, run headlong into his kingdome. And now he
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:17903:49"/> tempteth thee to doubt of thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ation; it is then because him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elfe doubteth of thy destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Of the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses mouing him to doubt.</hi>
                  </note> But whence (I pray thee) ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Deuill occasion thus to trouble thy minde? What is the matter, that thou fearest, lest thou be none of Gods children? <note place="margin">1. <hi>Worldly calamities.</hi>
                  </note> Gladly would I be a Simon, if it so pleased God, to ease thee of thy heauy burthen. Is it because thou liuest in miseries, art crossed and persecuted in this world? Thou thinkest, that God wil not deale so with those which loue him, and whom he loueth again? But thou shouldest consider, that thou art good ground, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore must often be plowed, and twy-fallowed, and harrowed, that thou maiest bring forth much fruit: <hi>the plowers</hi> (saith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) <note place="margin">Psal. 129</note>
                  <hi>plowed vpon my backe, and made long furrowes.</hi> Thou art a
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:17903:50"/> sheepe of Christs fold; whose fleece must yeerely be taken off; and must often goe in hard pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture, abiding heat and cold; winde and tempest, for thou art not to be killed, but kept. Thou art one of Gods children: <note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> and what sonne is it, whom the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chasteneth not? But if wee endure chastening, God offereth himselfe vnto vs, as vnto sonnes. Yea, <note place="margin">Reuel. 21.</note>
                  <hi>God shall</hi> (in heauen) <hi>wipe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all teares from our eyes:</hi> and how should they be wiped away, vnlesse wee first shed them here on earth? Did not the king of Heauen and Earth liue heere in pouerty, hauing not a place whereon to lay his head? Was not hee malitiously sclandered, and called a seditious person, a friend of Publicans and sinners, yea, a worker with Beelzebub the Prince of the Deuils? And was not hee betrayed by his familiar
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:17903:50"/> friend, mocked, spitted on, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n with staues, buffeted with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>istes; and hauing a murtherer preferred before him, at last con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to the shamefull death of the Crosse? Now, as S. Paul saith, <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> God hath <hi>predestinate vs to be made like to the image of his Son,</hi> and is God therefore angry with vs, because hee makes vs like to his beloued Sonne Iesus Christ? Surely, happy is our estate, that we are in this world appointed as sheep to the slaughter: for would we not willingly goe to Heauen with all speed? And, vnlesse wee were killed, when should wee die and goe thither, seeing we seldom run into any excesse, and haue most commonly light hearts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that charge of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle, <note place="margin">1. Thess. 5.</note>
                  <hi>Reioyce alwayes?</hi> Beare it patiently then (deare brother) whatsoeuer the Lord layeth on thee, as being a great token of his
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:17903:51"/> good-will: and comfort thy selfe in this, that he is a skilfull Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, which throughly knoweth the disease, the medicine, and the Patients strength; neither will lay more vpon vs, then hee will giue vs grace to beare.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Often falling into sinne.</hi>
                  </note> Is it, because of thy often slips and infirmities? Thou many times grieuously offendest God? But tell me one thing: dost thou goe with a full intent to sin, and not rather to doe good; howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vpon occasion, through the temptation of the Deuill, and frailty of thine owne flesh, thou fallest into some sinne? If thou dost, then art thou like Paul, which saith: <note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note>
                  <hi>I doe not the good thing, which I would; but the euill, which I would not, that doe I.</hi> Dost thou wish from thine heart, that thou couldest abstaine from sin, and lead a more godly life? If thou dost, then maist thou be
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:17903:51"/> sure, who ruleth at the heart: sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, the Deuill hath the outward roomes, yet the holy Ghost hath the in most. Thou art sorrie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause thou canst not doe so much good, as thou wouldest: &amp; I should be sorrie, if thou wouldest not doe more good, then S. Paul himselfe could. Consider I pray thee, that thou hatest sinne: and moreouer, that thou louest goodnesse, and therefore God who is goodnesse it selfe; who also being a searcher of the heart, seeth that thou louest him. And now, should God hate thee, which art his friend, when he so tenderly loued his enemies, that he gaue his only Son to death for them? Couldest thou loue God, vnlesse hee had loued thee first? Doubt thou not, Christ hath died for thy sins: for thou hatest sin, &amp; louest goodnes from the heart: a special marke of a good Christian.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3. <hi>Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>aces.</hi>
                  </note> Is it, because thou seest thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:17903:52"/> pride, malice, couetousnesse, &amp;c. and feelest the want of faith, &amp; other good graces of Gods spirit? But wouldst thou be without those inward corruptions? Art thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most sicke at the heart after Gods graces? And doest thou not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue now, that the grace of God dwelleth in thee? Yea, it is a great grace of God, to feele the want of Gods graces in thy selfe, &amp; to hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thirst after them: it is in a maner the possession of all graces; for <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atth. 5.</note>
                  <hi>Blessed are they which hunger and thirst after righteousnes, for they shall be satisfied.</hi> Christ hath said it, who is the truth and cannot lie; <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>h. 1.</note> who is the fountaine of graces, and of whose fulnes thou must receiue. Indeed, as touching the time when thou shalt be fully satisfied, it is in the world to come, and not in this world. For if being hungrie and thirstie, thou hast meat and drinke as much as thou wouldest, thy
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:17903:52"/> hunger and thirst after this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y food will be gone: so, if thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ouldest haue Gods graces, which are the spirituall foode of thy soule in as great plenty as thou couldest desire, thou wouldest not hunger nor thirst any more after them; which Christ knowing, hee will alwaies keepe thee hungry.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">4. <hi>Gods withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his graces for a time.</hi>
                  </note> Is it, because thou wast once wel disposed, thou couldest som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time pray heartily, and diddest feele the Comforter in thee: but since, thou hast grieuously offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded God, and now for a long time thy prayers haue been cold, neither canst thou haue any such comfortable feelings as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; which causeth thee greatly to feare, lest God hath wholly withdrawen his grace from thee? Surely, this befalleth many a man, and (no doubt) did befall Dauid after his adultery. What
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:17903:53"/> inward comfort (is it like) he had? What cold prayers did he make for a long time? But, consider with thy selfe, whether God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing sent some vnto thee, as hee sent Nathan vnto Dauid; <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sam. 12. Psal. 51.</note> thou dost confesse, <hi>I haue sinned;</hi> and wouldest be <hi>stablished with Gods free Spirit?</hi> If thou wouldest, then assure thy selfe, that doing as Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid did, thou shalt haue as Dauid had, thy sinne pardoned, and a right spirit renued in thee. Thou hast been indeed a prodigall son, but now feeling the smart of it, art willing to returne home againe: and should not thy father then receaue thee? <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uk. 15.</note> Yes (brother mine) when thou art yet a great way off, thy father will see thee, and haue compassion, and run, and fall on thy necke, and all to kisse thee. Thou hast beene a wandring sheepe, and Christ thy good Sheep-heard hath long sought
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:17903:53"/> thee, and called vnto thee by the mouth of his Preachers; but thou wouldst not be found, thou wouldest not heare for a long season: and now hearing, and being found, and willing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne; should he then leaue thee behind him? No, thinke not so: he will lay thee on his shoulders with ioy, and bring thee backe to thy fellowes. <note place="margin">Luk. 15.</note> Thou hast grieued the holy Ghost, <note place="margin">Ephes. 4.</note> wherewith thou wast sealed vnto the day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: wherfore he hath kept close, he hath hid himselfe for a long time, and thou hast wanted the seale or assurance of thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. But feare not, the seale shall be renued, the holy Ghost will shew himselfe againe: for, he would winne the house, though it was altogether vnwilling to be wonne; and would he not keepe the house, when it was in some measure willing to bee kept? He
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:17903:54"/> could winne the house, though it held with the Deuill; and could hee not keepe the house, when it held with himselfe? Call to minde that saying of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; <note place="margin">Psal. 77.</note>
                  <hi>I did consider the dayes of old, &amp; the yeers of ancient time. I called to remembrance my song in the night: I communed with mine owne heart, and my spirit searched dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently. Will the Lord absent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe for euer? and will he shew no more fauour? Is his mercy cleane gone for euer? and doth his promise faile for euermore? Hath God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten to be mercifull? hath he shut vp his tender mercies in displeasure? And I said, This is my death: yet I remembred the yeeres of the right hand of the most High.</hi> Thinke (good brother) thinke euen now thus with thy selfe. I doe well remember, o Lord my God, when thou wast in the house, when I felt thee at mine
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:17903:54"/> heart; and surely thou art the stronger: o Lord God, what a comfort should this be to a man in my case, though hee felt thee there but once in all his life time! The stronger man, I know well, had once also the house on his side. Comfort thy selfe (good brother) with this meditation; for I cannot but greatly reioyce ouer thee, as well knowing, that thou art still the child of God: indeed, that thou thy selfe doest not know it assuredly, but doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, yea happily euen despairest of it; God knoweth, that I pitty this thy present estate, and would if it lay in mee, refresh thy trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled spirit. Consider then, how God doth pitty thee, how he is both able, and willing to helpe thee. Hath man created, redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or sanctified? hath man taken so much paines about thee? But thy God hath done all
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:17903:55"/> this: God the Father is hee that created thee; Iesus Christ is hee that redeemed thee; the holy Ghost is hee that sanctified thee, which tooke such paines to driue the strong man forth. And now, being created, and redeemed, and sanctified, God keepe his seruant from thinking, that God will loose so much labour, and hee should euen be wholly forsaken. Tell mee, I pray thee, this one thing: Hast thou not now a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging desire to bee in thy former estate? And dost thou not then perceiue, that thou art not indeed forsaken, &amp; that the holy Ghost beginneth to shew himself again? For, who else can stirre vp this good desire? <note place="margin">Cor. 3.</note> Thou canst not of thy selfe so much as thinke a good thought: it commeth not then from thy selfe, much lesse is it the Deuils doing: it commeth therefore from the holy Ghost,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:17903:55"/> who will shew himselfe in greater measure than euer hee did; I know he will, it is his manner, he serueth others so. When hee is grieued by vs, hee will hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe for a time, that wee may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of grieuing him afterward. Doubt thou not, hee will shew himselfe againe, onely doe thou carefully vse the meanes to bring him forth of his closet: heare sermons, read good bookes, goe to some godly man for his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, be he ten, twenty, yea forty miles from thee; and neuer cease day nor night to call vpon thy God, that he would remember his old louing kindnesse. And then, as our Sauiour Christ saith; <note place="margin">Luk. 11.</note>
                  <hi>If yee which are euill, can giue good gifts to your children, how much more shall your heauenly Father giue the holy Ghost to them, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire it of him?</hi> Consider the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the poore widow, <note place="margin">Luk. 18.</note> who
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:17903:56"/> through hir importunitie obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hir suit of the wicked Iudge euen halfe against his will: and should not that good God, who delighteth in doing vs good, and so often calleth vpon vs to call vpon him in all our necessities, heare thy petitions, if thou bee importunate, as one that wil haue no deniall? Pray (good brother) pray continually: and feare not; for if God hauing brought the Israelites out of Egypt, should not haue brought them into that good land, <note place="margin">Num. 14. 16.</note> the Heathen would haue blasphemed his name, and said, that he wanted power to do it. Take then a good heart vnto thee: thy saluation is now ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the glory of God: hee that neuer left any thing vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, shal in his good time perfect that good worke which he hath begun in thee, euen for his owne name sake, onely forget not to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:17903:56"/> call vpon him. O Lord God, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his eyes that he may see how much he hath already receiued: and (good Lord) encrease in him and in vs all, faith in thee, zeale of thy glory, and loue to our brethren; that men seeing thy childrens good workes heere on earth, may glorifie thee our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which art in heauen. Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. An admonition to the carelesse Christian, remoouing the causes of his presumption.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>An admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to the carel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Christian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> TO the presumptuous and carelesse Christian, o Lord God, what might a man say, that would doe him any good! For if I should say, that he is no good Christian, and that he belieueth not in thee, I perswade my selfe, that he would not belieue mee so saying; alas, without thy speciall
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:17903:57"/> grace he will not surely perceiue his danger, which is the first step of auoiding the same. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>us I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e heard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>e to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ake.</hi>
                  </note> Thou that hast a strong faith, and euer had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest: thou that wouldest not so much as once doubt of thy sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation for the whole world: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, I pray thee; Is thy faith at this time strong? Dost thou not euen now doubt of thy saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Happy indeed wast thou, if thou diddest not doubt: but mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable art thou, that alwayes doubting, yea euen despairing, thou doest not perceiue thy des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate case. Thy mind hath euer been at quiet, thou neuer fearedst, what shall become of thee: no maruell, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.</note> though the fishers of men could not preuaile; for sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the best fishing is in troubled waters, then shall our Masters net soonest lay hold. <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 8.</note> Thy lying hart saith vnto thee, peace, peace, when there is no true peace.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:17903:57"/> Thou thinkest with thy selfe, <note place="margin">Reuel. 3.</note>
                  <hi>I am rich and increased with goods, &amp; haue need of nothing; and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est not, how thou art wretched, and miserable, and poore, and blind, and naked.</hi> Thou that art whole in thine owne eyes; how shouldest thou seeke to the Physitian? Thou that feelest not the want of faith; how canst thou pray, <note place="margin">Luk. 17.</note>
                  <hi>O Lord increase my faith?</hi> Is there not more hope of a foole, than of one wise in his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit? For with lesse adoe may that other bee taught wisdome, than this man so much as to know his owne follie. Learne then to become a foole, that thou maist be made wise: learne to know thy griefe, that thou maist seeke for helpe; to feele the want of faith, that thou maist pray God to giue it thee. Which to the end thou mightest doe, let vs a little examine thine estate:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:17903:58"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Of the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him to presume.</hi>
                  </note> How doest thou know, that thou hast a good faith, and shalt be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? Thou beleeuest, that Iesus Christ died for some mens sins: The reprobate; yea the Deuils beleeue this, and yet tremble for feare, which thou (it may bee) doest not. Thou must beleeue (man) that Iesus Christ died for thy sinnes: and, how doest thou know, that thou so beleeuest? <note place="margin">1. <hi>The multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>de.</hi>
                  </note> If most that haue heard it, could beleeue it, and by faith applie Christs death vnto themselues: would our Sauiour haue said, <note place="margin">Luk. 18.</note>
                  <hi>When the Sonne of man commeth, shall he finde faith on the earth?</hi> It is an easie matter to beleeue in him, and let him come when hee will, he shall finde inough in all places, which haue a strong faith, and euer had: but, how then doth hee aske, whether hee shall now finde faith on the earth? Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he or we (assure thy selfe) are
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:17903:58"/> greatly dceiued. Call to minde the daies of Noah, how few god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were then liuing: consider the time of Christs first comming, whether he came not among his owne, &amp; they receiued him not: and now he complaineth of the small number of beleeuers at his second comming to iudgement. Our Sauiour is hee that saueth, and he knoweth whom hee shall saue: hee it is in whom wee must beleeeue, &amp; should not he know who beleeueth? should not hee know his owne? Thou doest (I hope) beleeue him, in whom (as thou faiest) thou doest beleeue: few men then haue a true faith, few shall enter in at the strait gate: and, how doest thou know assuredly, that thou art one of those few? I greatly feare lest this thy perswasion was grounded on the multitude: thou liuedst as well as the most, and therefore
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:17903:59"/> haddest as good a faith, and shouldest be saued assoone. Was it not so, I pray thee? Hast thou not thought thus with thy selfe? Examine thine owne hart (man) whether thou hast or not: and consider that few finde the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row way to heauen: <note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> this world for many, and the next for few; euen as the earth <note place="margin">2. Esdr. 8.</note>
                  <hi>giueth much earthly matter to make pots and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle dust that gold commeth of.</hi> But heere thou wilt happily say: and should not God then be a cruell tyrant? No, God forbid: hee is the father of mercies, his mercy is infinite: he put his Sonne, his only Sonne, his beloued Sonne, to death for his enemies; <note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> and should he then be cruell to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde? Consider, what wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mercy he daily sheweth thee, euery time thou willingly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest him, be it in the misse-spen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of an houre, or deceiuing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:17903:59"/> thy neighbour of a pennie, or such like. Doest thou not then esteeme the profit of a penny be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his fauour, thou being dust, and hee a God of maiestie; yea, when thou doest beleeue, that he put his Sonne to death for that and other thy sinnes? Doest thou not abuse his good creature to his owne dishonour; nay, to the honour of his and thine vtter aduersarie, the Deuill? Doest thou not doe it in his presence, when hee telleth thy conscience of it, when thou knowest that he seeth thee; nay, when he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that thou art not ignorant, he is aware of it? And yet thou wilt sinne, onely because hee is mercifull, for otherwise thou durst not: what an horrible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation is this? But yet consider further, <note place="margin">Iob 35.</note> that he is God all suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: if he did punish thee, thou couldest not hurt him: if hee
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:17903:60"/> should spare thee, thou couldest not profit him? And, is it not then wonderfull mercie, that hee spareth thee one only time? And now, how many thousand times? Gods mercie is infinite: but see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he sheweth such mercie vnto thee, when thou takest no notice of it; beware, lest when thou loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest for mercie heereafter, thou findest him a seuere Iudge, in stead of a mercifull Father. And to the end the wonderfull great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Gods mercie vnto man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde in this world might the better appeare; adde heereunto, what dutifulnesse many of vs looke for at our seruants hands, as that they must not speake an idle word or looke awry in our presence: for if we could endure them to abuse vs, our abusing of God were not so intolerable. We need not the Queene of the South or any other, <note place="margin">Mat. 12.</note> to rise vp in
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:17903:60"/> iudgement, and to condemne vs: euery mans owne example may suffice to condemne himselfe to the pit of hell, seeing wee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme more obedience vnto man, when a greater than man is alwaies present. I say nothing, what traiterous mindes many beare vnto God: how that they could wish in their hearts, there were no God at all, that so they might die as other creatures doe, and neuer come to iudgement: or else, that the Deuill were in his roome, that so, if they are Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, they might take bribes; if Ministers, they might neglect their dutie; if of any estate what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, they might passe their time in drunkennesse, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, dancing, dicing, &amp;c. and yet, as dutifull seruants to such a master, be sure to come to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen afterward. Examine thine owne conscience well touching
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:17903:61"/> this matter, gentle Reader: and if thy heart condemne thee here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, vnderstand, <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.</note> that God is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than thy heart, and knoweth all things. What wonderfull mercie then is it, that he suffereth such a traitour to liue one day to an end? Surely, as one faith, Gods mercie in this world seemeth to be follie, and his iustice in the next will seeme to be furie. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though indeed they are not so: for God is not as man, and both his mercie and iustice are accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his nature, which is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite. But not to stand longer heereupon: if thou wouldest thorowly consider, how intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly God is heere abused, thou wilt bee so farre from thinking, either that God is not mercifull, or that few men shall bee saued: as that thou wilt wonder, how God can bee so mercifull, as to saue euen a very few of vs; but
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:17903:61"/> indeed his mercie is wonderfull to mankinde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>The learned.</hi>
                  </note> Relie not now vpon the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; no, nor yet vpon the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as though liuing as they doe, thou wast in safetie. For whiles we be young plants, we are rather bowed to Aristotle, than to Christ: lesse care is had, that wee follow Christ in manners, than Aristotle in opinions; and as we are then bowed, many of vs grow euer after. Then learne wee such cunning to deceiue others, that in the end wee deceiue our owne selues: if God say, Few men shall be saued; wee say, Hee doth not meane so, it is onely to feare vs, and yet we will not be feared nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. When wee first reade the Scriptures, and see Gods threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings against sinners, we shall be much mooued for a time, the holy Ghost will make the house to quake for feare: but if he doth
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:17903:62"/> not win the house at some three or foure assaults, the Deuill in short time will so fortifie it; that reade we neuer so many threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, see we neuer such fearefull examples, wee shall bee mooued nothing at all. Hast not thou, which knowest little, done some things against thy knowledge? Why should it then seeme strange, if those which know more, doe many things against theirs? Yea, often times they which read the Scriptures most, practise least of that they reade: for seeing they haue still in their hands Gods word, <note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note>
                  <hi>the keies of the kingdome of heauen;</hi> the Deuill will lay more bolts on their heeles to presse them downe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell, and will not be content to haue them liue as bad onely as other men doe. Thinke not then with thy selfe; If I liue as some great learned man doth, I shall
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:17903:62"/> be saued: lest making part of the Deuils chaine, hee should hold one linke fast; and then surely all others fastened thereunto, will follow headlong into the pit of destruction. Another mans wicked life shall not saue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, much lesse shall it saue thee; it must be thine owne good life, and nothing else. Ground not thy saluation vpon anothers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction: fetch not thy assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from the vices in other men, but rather from Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in thy selfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3. <hi>Good motions, and a qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> conscienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> And so happily thou doest af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a sort: for thou thinkest; I haue often times good motions: I am no common drunkard, swearer, lier, theefe, &amp;c. my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science doth not accuse me. But as touching thy good motions, know, that the most wicked haue them, vnlesse they be giuen ouer to a reprobate sense. The holy
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:17903:63"/> Ghost indeede assaulteth the house: but, doth the house yeeld to his assaults? Doest thou put in practise, what the holy Ghost putteth into thy minde? He that shooteth a bullet into a castle, and causeth it to shake or mooue, (for thou speakest of thy good motions) hath not straightway gotten possession: but if a man shoot a bullet foorth of a castle, this is a sure token that hee is within. <note place="margin">Luk. 6.</note> What good now out of the treasure of thine heart, hast thou brought foorth? None at all from thy heart, I warrant thee. And as touching thy small offenses, for which thy consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth not accuse thee: it is, because thou hast now a dead conscience; which will then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to liue, when thou begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest to die. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>science, and a good qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> A dead quiet consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will not accuse a man, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse for some horrible sins,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:17903:63"/> as murder, adulterie, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, whoredome, and such like: but a good quiet conscience will accuse a man for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ry willi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> sinne, vntill he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> forgiuenesse, and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> quiet. Thy dead consci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not comfort thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any more▪ but a good cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuall feast, the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of no man kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> It may be, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with thy selfe; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wicked man. I should not so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper in this world. And doest thou not remember, how that Diues was clothed in purple, and fared delicately euery day, <note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> and <hi>receiued</hi> (marke the word) his pleasures heere in his life time? Call to minde, what the Prophet saith of the wicked; <note place="margin">Psal. 73.</note>
                  <hi>They are not in trouble as others are: neither are they plagued with other men:</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:17903:64"/>
                  <hi>their eies stand out with fatnesse: they haue more than heart can wish.</hi> Thou art fatted (man) against the day of slaughter. Consider with thy selfe: what care hast thou had of thy saluation? Hast thou not cared more for thy swine, than for Christ? for this world, than for the world to come? Thou wilt happily denie it in words: but, examine thy deeds, I aduise thee; for God will not beleeue thy words, if thy workes shew the contrary. Hast thou sought as earnestly for eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life at any time heeretofore, as thou wouldest seeke at this time for thy swine, were they lost; <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>m. 9.</note> or, as Saul did once seeke for his fathers asses, who went from place to place, &amp; at length got him to the Seer, to learne of him, if hee did see, what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of them? And though thou hast gone from towne to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:17903:64"/> towne after Preachers; as a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ne man would follow Christ, <note place="margin">Luk. 9.</note>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ithersoeuer hee went; whose <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>art our Sauiour knowing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>sed his companie. Though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, thou hast after a sort de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to heare the word: as the Iewes would haue reioiced in Iohn Baptists light for a season, <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note> and went a great way to heare him: yet know, that <note place="margin">Luk. 13.</note>
                  <hi>many shall seeke to enter in at the strait gate, and shall not bee able.</hi> Doth thy conscience tell thee, that thou hast sought first and principally <note place="margin">Matt. 6.</note>
                  <hi>the kingdome of God, and the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse thereof?</hi> No, it doth not: thy affection hath beene most set on earthly things. And now, <note place="margin">Matt. 7.</note> seeing Christ forbiddeth vs to cast our pearles before swine: should hee giue the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, <note place="margin">Reuel. 21</note> a Citty built of gold and pretious stones, to those which esteeme so lightly of it?
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:17903:65"/> No, he will not: thy minde run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, not most commonly on this kingdome; a sure token, that it belongeth not to thee, that as yet thou art not heire apparent. If thou doest not so perswade thy selfe, examine well the grounds of thy contrary perswasion. Are they not, the multitude, the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, thy good motions without effect, thy dead conscience, and worldly prosperity? Thou hast no assurance from the holy Ghost, no loue to goodnesse, no feruancy in prayer, no inward consolation; in a word, no care of thy selfe. Happy mightest thou be, if thou haddest this only care, to perceiue thine owne care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesnesse, and what care God now hath of thee. <hi>A Sparrow</hi> (saith Christ) <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at. 10.</note>
                  <hi>shall not fall on the ground without your father:</hi> and should this booke come into thine hands without the prouidence of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:17903:65"/> God? It is of more value then many Sparrowes. Thou doest not looke (I hope) that God should send an Angel from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to warne thee; and now hee warneth the by a messenger: O Lord, giue him grace to thinke so of it. Call to minde thy life past: examine well thine owne waies: striue to see thine inward sinnes, to feele the want of Gods graces: keepe good company: heare Sermons, reade good bookes: call vpon God day and night for his grace. Why shouldest thou perish in thy sinnes, seeing God would not the death of a sinner, and now so lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingly doth call vnto thee? Should I be the cause of thy greater paines in Hell, whiles I seeke to bring thee to the ioyes of Heauen? Harden not thine heart like an adamant: stop not thine eares like the deafe Adder; <note place="margin">Psalm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> when
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:17903:66"/> thou maiest heare with thine eares, and vnderstand with thine heart, by what meanes thou shouldest be saued. (O Lord, do thou open his deafe eares, and mollifie his stony heart.) Wilt thou doe now, as I haue said? What answer doth thy consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence make to him that sent mee, and to him which created thee, who is also here present, euen in this very place? Thou dost not see him? For indeed, he is <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>The word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>irit) is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> plaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>glish, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>de or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ath,</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>fieth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>h. Iohn</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>gh God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>alled a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>suming Deut.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4. <hi>yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>y is he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ed a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>de, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>th; as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ch doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, inuisible, as the winde or aire, which vnseene goeth euen to thine heart it selfe. But (I pray thee) dost thou not feele him? doth hee not now moue thine heart? doth he not now assault the house? Faine would he win it: hee is the stronger man: hee can driue the Diuell forth; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do thou beware of taking part with the Deuill. Consider (man) that thou hast a soule to saue: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:17903:66"/> that thou hast but a short time to saue it; this life is a moment, whereupon hangeth all eternity. Hast thou now any care of thy selfe? Wouldest thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed faine be saued? Doe then but thorowly examine thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state at this time. If thou dost thus; know, that the holy Ghost hath won one roome already: and alwaies, when hee moueth thee to pray, to heare or read Gods word, to giue almes, to doe good or abstaine from euill; yeeld to his good motions, and thinke thus with thy selfe. Now doth the holy Ghost assault the house: now would he faine win one roome more. And if thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies yeeldest vnto him, thou shalt see, that winning one roome after another, he will soone driue the Deuill out of all, euen to thy euerlasting and vnspeakeable comfort.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:17903:67"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. Of certain impediments, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the carelesse Christian from giuing entertainment to the holy Ghost, and reforming his life.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>taine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>nts.</hi>
                  </note> BVt here I am not ignorant, what the old Serpent sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth to thy minde: namely, that hereafter thou wilt hearken to this good counsell, and obey the good inspirations of Gods spirit. Thou art now poore, and wouldest first gather riches; or young, and wouldest first come to some yeeres: then (if it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth God) thou wilt reforme thy life, and become a new man; but wheras it best pleaseth him, thou shouldest euen now amend, that thou wilt not do by any meanes. And art thou indeed perswaded, that thou shalt then doe it with
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:17903:67"/> greater ease? <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pouerty.</hi>
                  </note> Thou hast not (I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>st) forgotten, what answer some made, when they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto supper. <note place="margin">Luk. 14.</note>
                  <hi>I haue bought a Farme, and I must needes goe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e it: I pray thee haue me excused. I haue bought fiue yoke of Oxen, and I goe to prooue them: I pray thee haue me excused.</hi> When thou hast gotten a Farme, or Oxen, or the like; then maist thou well be excused from comming, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing other matters to looke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Then thou wilt thinke with thy selfe, as no doubt many of our rich men doe thinke in these daies. If I were a poore man, I would surely haue a care to please God; that seeing in this world I could not, I might liue pleasant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the world to come: but it must not seene strange, that I haue now more care to please my selfe. Indeed, I am more behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto God, then such a one
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:17903:68"/> is: but I can haue a kingdome out of hand, and therefore no maruel, though I prefer it before a kingdome hereafter. <note place="margin">Mat. 19.</note> Diddest thou neuer heare of a certaine rich man, who not being guilty to himselfe of the breach of any commandement euen from his youth; yet came running with speed vnto Christ, that he might learne, if any thing were wanting? What one rich man in these daies may in any sort be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto him? And yet, when one thing was lacking, he went away sorrowfully: whereupon our Sauiour vttered that feareful saying, which made his Disciples, though poore men, exceedingly amazed; It <hi>is easier for a Camell to goe through the eye of a needle, then for a rich man to enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</hi> I know well, that all things are possible with almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God: but, were it not a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:17903:68"/> to see a Camel going thorow a needles eye? It is a wonder then if any rich-man in the world be saued: and God sheweth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders seldome, for were they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, they should not be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Surely, when riches en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, men lightly set their hearts vnto them: and God by no meanes will suffer Mammon to come into his kingdome. Riches cause men to swell with pride: and is it for a swollen man to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in at a straight gate? Nay ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, he must rather be sicke of a consumption, and be nothing in his owne eyes. Riches make men high minded, and heauen gate is too low: they which meane to goe in thereat, must learne of Christ to be humble and lowly of heart. Few, I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant thee, encrease so fast in goods, but they decrease as fast in goodnesse. And moreouer, if
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:17903:69"/> thou gettest goods honestly, thou maiest aswell doe it after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: if wrongfully, then must thou repay them, when thou hast truly repented, or else thy conscience will neuer be quiet. With what face canst thou say; I thanke thee (ô God) for this meat, this clothing &amp;c. when thy conscience shall tell thee in the meane season, that happily thou art beholding to the Deuill for it? A little leauen leaueneth the whole lumpe; and so doth a litle goods wrongfully gotten: for thou canst not say of any, This I haue honestly; seing if thou haddest no ill gotten goods, thou shouldest it may be, haue done away that. Wherfore, when thou commest to meat, let this be thy grace: I thanke thee (o Lord) for this meat, vnlesse I am beholding to the Deuill for it. And if thou bee ashamed to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:17903:69"/> say thus, then must thou make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutiō, for at leastwise thou shalt thinke thus. Yea, marke whether thou dost not thinke so the next time thou commest to table, if thou hast iniuried any man in his goods, and thy conscience be not altogether dead. Dost thou not see, that when saluation was come to Zaccheus his house, <note place="margin">Luk. 19.</note> Christ the Sauiour being entred thereinto, that hee stood forth and said; <hi>Behold, Lord, the halfe of my goods I giue to the poore: and if I haue taken from any man by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged cauillation, I restore him foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold?</hi> Oh that our couetous worldlings would now lay vp this in their hearts; that if euer salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion come to their houses, and that Christ the Sauiour dwelleth in them by his Spirit, <note place="margin">Ro. 8. 19 Luk. 16.</note> the riches of iniquitie gotten by iniquitie must bee thrust out of doores, and three times asmuch with it,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:17903:70"/> for feare lest any should remaine behind! It would cause them to tremble, being as yet worldly minded, to offer the least iniurie whatsoeuer. In a word: were he not a foolish thiefe, that would keepe his stollen goods, both in the sight of his accuser &amp; iudge? A mans conscience now is his accuser, and God his iudge, and both know of it: when therefore he becommeth wise vnto saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he shall make restitution assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly. If thou hast first restored thy heart vnto God, thou wilt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward restore euery mans goods vnto himselfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Young <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>eres.</hi>
                  </note> As touching the other impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment, thy young yeeres; thou hast great cause to reioyce ouer them: for being a young plant, thou maiest easily be bowed any way; whereas comming to some yeeres, thou wilt rather breake than bowe. Then thou wilt say,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:17903:70"/> as others now doe: Wee are too old to learne any goodnes: our sinnes haue taken such hold on vs, that we can by no meanes cast them off: this spirituall sicknes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>th runne on so long, that wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e euen now dead in our sinnes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ltogether past cure, there is no hope of recouerie. Indeed, if the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound had been looked too in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime, before it was festered, then (no doubt) some good might haue been done. Oh, how many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re there, which running in the way to hell, do first come to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ourneyes end; before the time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e come, wherein they meant to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et one foot forward towards the kingdome of heauen! There are some, which prefixing no certain time of repentance, put off all vntill the last day, come when it will. But seeing they had need to heare Gods word all that day, and pray all that day, and giue
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:17903:71"/> thankes all that day, and giue almes all that day, and visit the sicke all that day, and (in a word) perform all the duties of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian all that day long, and yet all too litle: how strangely (I pray thee) should that last day be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stered with good works? Others there are, which will aske but one houre before death: and if they haue time to say, <hi>Lord haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on vs,</hi> it is inough, they shall be saued. But doe they not heare, that many shall say, <note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note>
                  <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> which shall not enter into the kingdome of heauen? And here I would aske them, how they know assuredly, that they shall haue an houre? They may dye suddenly: or else their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing and memorie may faile them; for in the iust iudgment of God, they which in their life time willingly forget him, at their deaths many times forget
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:17903:71"/> themselues. But be it, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of these befall: doe they thinke it so easie a matter to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent them truly of their sinnes? Indeed, were the repentance, which God requireth, only from the lips outward, I could not much blame them so to imagin; for it is an easie matter to say, I repent: but this is a repentance (as they shall one day finde) to be repented of for euermore. Heare what the Prophet saith, <hi>At what time soeuer a sinner doth repent him of his sinnes from the bottome of his heart, &amp;c.</hi> and there is a great distance between the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the heart and the lips, as euery one well knoweth. <hi>Poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia dicitur quasi punientia:</hi> and surely <hi>poenitet quem poena tenet,</hi> he onely repenteth that is pained at the heart for his iniquities. When as the remembrance of thy sinnes doth so much grieue
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:17903:72"/> thine heart, as the committing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them did reioyce the same heere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tofore: then doest thou repen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> according to the will of God▪ this, and this onely is that repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance which remission of sinnes doth accompanie. Thy heart must be pricked, as theirs were, of whom we read in the Actes of the Apostles: <note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> it must bee rent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunder, as the Prophet willeth; <hi>Rent your hearts, and not your gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 51.</note> it must bee wounded, as Dauids was; <hi>A broken and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart shalt thou not despise:</hi> so that the very bloud issue forth, I meane, teares; for <hi>Lachrimae sunt animae sanguis;</hi> but then they must be <hi>amarae,</hi> bitter teares, as Peters were, <hi>who went forth and wept bitterly.</hi> And to the end thou mightest not bee deceiued: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider I pray thee, what griefe and sorrow thou hast sustained here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, for the losse of thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:17903:72"/> children, or by reason of any other great calamitie that hath befallen thee. To grieue thus at any worldly crosse, it is of nature: but it is of grace, thus to grieue for thy sinnes, in asmuch as they are such; I adde, in as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they are such. For I am not ignorant, that Saul &amp; Ahab were sorry for their transgressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15 1. King. 21.</note> in asmuch as they were a meanes to pull downe the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God vpon their heads.</p>
               <p>And now hearken to good counsell. In this weeke follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing make triall, whether thou canst thus repent, that is, grieue for thine iniquities, whereupon amendment of life, as an effect hereof, ensueth immediatly. What a folly, or madnesse ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were it for thee in a matter of such weight, to presume that thou shalt bee able to repent at
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:17903:73"/> the last gaspe: and not to make proofe aforehand in thy life time, whether it be in thy power so to doe, or not? If vpon triall this next weeke thou findest, that thou hast so much grace at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: then shall it be lawful for thee afterward to returne with the sowe that is washed to thy wallowing againe in the mire, if thou wilt; I say, If thou wilt; as being well assured thou wilt not. For how should that heart, which hath been pricked, rent asunder, and euen broken to pieces for sinne, euer be willing to commit sinne, for which it should bee pricked, rent asunder, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to pieces againe? On the contrarie side: if vpon triall thou findest, that thy stony heart refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth to be smitten: or being smit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in some sort, yet by reason of the hardnesse thereof will not cleaue asunder, that so the bitter
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:17903:73"/> waters may flow out abundantly: then it stands thee vpon to repēt thee of thy folly in delaying thy repentance, and betimes to looke about thee; lest that time which God hath <hi>giuen thee to repent in,</hi> should bee past; <note place="margin">Reuel. 2. Heb. 12.</note> and then with Esau thou shalt finde no place of repentance, though thou care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully seekest it with teares. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not thy selfe: this hearty sorrow for sinne, this rew, this hearbe of grace, seldome or neuer growes vpon a sudden, as Ionah his gourd did, vnlesse it be miraculously: and were it not a wonder, that thou shouldest be saued by a miracle?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiect: 1.</label>
                  <hi>Ob:</hi> Did not the thiefe repent on a sudden at the last gaspe, and obtaine mercy at the hands of God? Answ: True: but we haue not the like example againe throughout the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Now then, seeing one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:17903:74"/> so late, we haue cause not to despaire of any, and to hope and pray still for their conuersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But seeing it was one onely, and no more; thou hast farre greater cause to feare, that thou shalt not be another: thou I say, which I feare me in one respect art worse than the thiefe. For he as it seemeth, before this time had no knowledge of Christ, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did wilfully and desperately so long delay the meanes of his saluation: wheras thou canst not pretend ignorance, and yet when Christ <hi>standeth without at the doore, and knocketh</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 3.</note> (as now I hope he doth) offering thee grace to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend thy former life; through the hardnes of thine heart thou shuttest the doore against him, giuing him his answere without, and saying vnto him as it were. Lord, I am not willing to haue thy companie so long: keep thy
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:17903:74"/> grace with thy self yet for a time: but come againe heereafter when my time is almost past, and for a litle time I am content to giue thee entertainment. Thou vile ingratefull wretch, which doest belieue, that God will haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon thee repenting so late; and yet canst finde in thy wicked heart to offend so good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a God one houre to an end.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Obiect: 2.</label>
                  <hi>Ob:</hi> Hath not God said, <hi>At what time soeuer a sinner doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent him of his sinnes from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of his heart, I will put all his wickednesse out of my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance?</hi> Answ: It is true, but hee hath not further said; <hi>&amp; at what time soeuer a sinner will hee can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent him of his sinnes from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of his heart.</hi> Nay, thou shalt finde that true, which a godly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther saith; <hi>God, who hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed grace at any time to the poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:17903:75"/>
                  <hi>hath not promised a man grace to repent at any time.</hi> If for all that can be said, thou still presumest, that it is in thy power to repent at thy pleasure: then if thou wilt, thou canst amend straightway; but this thou wilt not, and then belike God must tarry thy lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. Should thy sonne abuse thee euery houre, and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, why hee did so; should answer, That an houre before death he would amend: wouldest thou take this for an answer? For, when death commeth, though hee would, yet can hee not abuse thee any longer. Let those which will not leaue their sinnes before death, take heed; lest when they would leaue their sinnes, their sinnes will not leaue them, but goe with them, and accuse them before Gods iudgement seat.</p>
               <p>To conclude. If thou being in
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:17903:75"/> thine house wast this day set vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by thine enemie; and after his departure, diddest feare his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe ere it were long: wouldest thou not very diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make vp the breaches, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie thine house in the best man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thou couldest deuise? Be not then so foolish, as to thinke the old Serpent not so politicke as thy selfe: hee will in time make the house (I warrant thee) euen invincible. Thou, whose heart I hope beginneth now to relent, and is almost battered with good inspirations from aboue: if at this time possession be not got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, take heed lest by litle &amp; litle it grow harder and harder, vntill at length thou be no more moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, than if a bullet were shot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a rocke of stone. Oh, how many haue we seen lying in their death beds, either not at all as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saulted by the holy Ghost; or if
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:17903:76"/> they be, yet their stonie hearts so obdurate, as that not the least impression may bee made in them!</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3. <hi>Atheisme.</hi> Psal. 14. Hebr. 11.</note> But thou art happily one of those fooles, which say in their hearts, <hi>There is no God:</hi> and then all my paines aforetaken should be altogether lost. For, <hi>Hee that that will come to God, must first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue that hee is:</hi> and surely (as it followeth in the Psalme) <hi>corrupt are they, and become abominable in their wickednesse, there is none</hi> (of these fooles) <hi>that doth good.</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not affirme, that there are any so foolish, as to say openly with their tongue, <hi>There is no God:</hi> for they well know, that there are men, which would not suffer such villanie vnpunished. But the number of those, which say in their hearts or thinke thus, is (I feare me) exceeding great, as their abominable doings sufficiently
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:17903:76"/> declare. I haue thought good therefore in this place briefly to answer the Deuils chiefest argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whereby hee goeth about to bring foolish men into this worse than diuelish minde, I say, worse than diuelish; for hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieueth, <note place="margin">Iam. 2.</note> that there is a God, though he would perswade men, that there were none.</p>
               <p>One of his arguments often vrged to many mens conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is; If there were a God, hee would not suffer the godly to liue heere in miserie, and the wicked contrariwise in prosperitie. But consider with thy selfe: whether those sheep, which thou meanest to kill, goe not in fat pasture; when others feed on the hard common? And againe, whether heauen was not more welcome to Lazarus, than it would haue been to the rich glutton? Indeed, we men punish our enemies, and
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:17903:77"/> pleasure our frinds, in this world; for when they are once dead, wee can doe neither: but there is no reason, wherefore God should thus deale; seeing he can reward his friends, and punish his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, for euer heereafter. And yet by his dealing with men in this life, we may well learne, that there is a God: seeing none of those horrible plagues befall the godly, which haue light vpon the wicked; as vpon Sodome, <note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> vpon Herod, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. 12.</note> and diuers others in these our daies.</p>
               <p>Another argument is: That we cannot see by our reason, how any thing should be, vnlesse it had a beginning, and were made; which none hold of God. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>r reason <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>th com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> vs to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>eeue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>t which<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> beyond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>son.</hi>
                  </note> And indeed, it is most true, that wee cannot see thus much by our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: but yet our reason doth teach vs, that there must needs be something, which had no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:17903:77"/> neither was made. For we know, that there is the world, and that we our selues are in the world. Now, either the world was made, and had beginning; or not: if not, then there is some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing already, that was not made, neither had beginning; namely, the world. If the contrary bee true; then, what made the world? For it could not make it selfe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse it were before it selfe. And then; what made that, which made the world? Againe, what made the last? Thus at length our reason will teach vs, that there must needs be something that was not made, nor had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning; and this indeed is God. If it be said: The world was from euerlasting. Then I say: This were a wonder, and beyond all reason of man: but yet it is farre more agreeable to reason, that one thing should be, and not be
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:17903:78"/> made; than many thousands, as Sunne, Moone, starres, birds, beasts, fishes, trees, and infinite other, all which haue not so much power, as to make one dust of nothing. But not to stand lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger heereupon: my counsell to the foole, if he be but reasonably wise, is; that so many beleeuing there is a God, and hee not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly knowing the contrary, that he would at leastwise doubt thereof, and therefore for feare of the worst (if for nothing else) would heare Sermons, reade good bookes, abstaine from euill, doe good, and liue order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, seeing it is not very trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some; whereas, if in the end it should fall out, that there is a God, his punishment for doing the contrary should bee excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding intolerable. Surely, were a man not altogether out of his wits, and stood in some little
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:17903:78"/> feare only, of being cast into our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re; he would not sticke to pricke his finger with a pinne, if hee had any hope at all, thereby to auoid the danger.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. Of the Deuils dealing with those, which by good bookes, or other meanes, are called to repentance.</head>
               <p>NOw then, to draw towards an end of this my discourse. Like as heeretofore God sent Moses to deliuer the Israelites from the tyrannie of Pharaoh and the Egyptians: so doe thou thinke, that at this time hee hath sent this booke to deliuer thee from the slauerie of the Deuill and his wicked Angels. And looke, what Pharaohs behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our was, before the Israelites could get out of his dominion: the like will the Deuils behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:17903:79"/> be, before thou shalt be freed from his subiection.</p>
               <p>When Moses and Aaron did their message vnto Pharaoh from the Lord, Pharaoh answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; <note place="margin">Exod. 5.</note>
                  <hi>Moses and Aaron, why cause yee the people to cease from their workes? get you to your burdens:</hi> and heereupon made their bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage more grieuous. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the officers came to Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh to complaine: but Pharaoh said vnto them; <hi>Idle, idle are yee; therefore ye say, Let vs goe offer sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice vnto the Lord.</hi> And so (as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure thy selfe) the Deuill thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, that I haue caused thee to cease from thy workes; thou mightest now haue beene about thy burdens, a spending thy time in drunkennesse, dicing, dancing, &amp;c. idle, idle hast thou beene, thou hast had too much leisure, or else thou wouldest not regard these vaine words. Wherefore
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:17903:79"/> the Deuill will goe about to lay more burdens on thee, hee will not be content to haue thee liue as bad as heeretofore, but will striue to bring thee more vnder his subiection. Beware of him therefore, I counsell thee: for hence is it, that in those places, where Gods word is most sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely preached; some liue more wickedly, than in any other. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though indeed, this also com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth partly from the nature of the glorious Gospell of Iesus Christ <hi>the Sunne of righteousnesse:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Malac. 4</note> which shining vpon one that hath any life, will more reuiue and quicken him; but if hee be altogether dead in sinne, it will cause him to stinke before the face of God and man.</p>
               <p>When God plagued Egypt, then Pharaoh began to yeeld, and would haue them offer sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Lord in his land. <note place="margin">Exod. 8▪ 25.</note> But
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:17903:80"/> this Moses hauing refused, and God continuing his plagues stil; Pharaoh said vnto Moses and Aaron: <note place="margin">Exod. 10. 11.</note>
                  <hi>Goe yee men</hi> (out of my land) <hi>and serue the Lord;</hi> but your children and cattle shall remaine behinde. And though the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill bee somewhat loth, yet at length he will peraduenture bee content, that thou shalt halfe serue God, so that thou wilt serue him as much. Thou shalt goe to the Church, and pray, and heare Gods word: but afterward, thou shalt goe to the tauerne, bowling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, &amp;c. and spend halfe thy time in drinking, swearing, and the like. For the Deuill is not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note>
                  <hi>no man can serue two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters:</hi> he well knoweth, that God is a true Father, which by no meanes will haue his childe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided.</p>
               <p>When Pharaoh saw, that one plague followed on anothers
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:17903:80"/> necke, and that with the froward, God delt frowardly: then said he vnto Moses; <note place="margin">Exod. 10 24.</note>
                  <hi>Goe, serue the Lord: only your sheepe and your cattle shall abide, and your children shall goe with you.</hi> And if there be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, then will the Deuill (though very loth) suffer thee wholly to serue the Lord, and to forsake all thy sinnes: onely thy couetousnesse, or drunkennesse, or whoredome, or dicing, &amp;c. onely one sinne shall abide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde. Pharaoh well knew, that where the Israelites treasure was, there was their heart also; and where their hart was, there would the whole body be ere it were long. And the Deuill is not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that if one sinne remaine behinde, the whole body of sinne may be brought in againe. Let Herod heare Iohn gladly, and reforme many things: but let him keepe his brothers wife, and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:17903:81"/> the Deuill will bring it so to passe, that Herod sorrowing, <note place="margin">Mark. 6.</note> and against his will, shall command Iohns head to be cut off. Let Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das bee an Apostle, and heare Christ, and preach the Gospell; <note place="margin">Matt. 10.</note> nay, let him cast Deuils out of others: but let him retaine a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous minde, and the Deuill will enter into Iudas himselfe, so that he shall be compelled to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray his owne master.</p>
               <p>When Moses would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this offer, but said, <hi>There shal not an hoofe be left:</hi> then was Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh presently in a rage. Then, <note place="margin">Exod. 10. 28.</note>
                  <hi>Get thee from mee: looke thou see my face no more: for whensoeuer thou commest in my sight, thou shalt die.</hi> Now, I see that <hi>euill is before your face:</hi> I well perceaue, you now intend some mischiefe: when you are once gotten out of Aegypt, you neuer meane to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne hither againe. And if thou
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:17903:81"/> wilt needes giue vp thy body <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note>
                  <hi>a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, holy, acceptable sacrifice vnto God;</hi> which accepteth no sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, vnlesse it be altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out spot and blemish: then will the Deuil presently take on: I am a Serpent, and if I can keepe in but my head, I doubt not of bringing my whole body in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. But, if thou wilt wholy shut me out, if thou wilt forsake all thy euill waies: then, euill is before thy face, thou surely mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest me no good: and then God best knoweth, what stir hee will keepe in some mens consciences. But let Pharaoh rage neuer so much, yet shall there not an hoofe be left in Egypt: and though the Deuill be euen mad with anger; yet doe not thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake God, and God will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake thee, vntill he hath brought thee wholly out of his subiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and giuen thee a willing
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:17903:82"/> minde to forsake all thy sinnes. Vntill which time, thou art not fit to offer thy selfe a sacrifice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord. For, if any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine behinde, <note place="margin">Exod. 10. 26.</note> either hand, eye, eare, &amp;c. how dost thou know, whether God will be serued with it, or not? And, how canst thou heartily pray to God for his grace, when thou wouldest not haue grace to forsake some sinne or other? I know well, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer the Israelites were wholly gotten out of Egypt; yet Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah did his vttermost to fetch them backe again: and although thou hast set thy selfe wholy to serue the Lord, yet wil the Deuill doe his endeuour to bring thee once more vnder his subiection. But, as Pharaoh with his army were ouerthrowen in the red sea: so shall the Deuill with his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels bee ouercome by <note place="margin">Reu. 12.</note>
                  <hi>the blood of the Lambe.</hi> I know also, that
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:17903:82"/> the Israelites loathing Manna, fell a lusting after the flesh-pots, the Onyons, and Garlicke of Egypt: and thou sometime be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euen weary of Gods graces, wilt peraduenture haue a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after thy former vile plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures. But their mercifull God did not take away their Manna, nor suffer them to returne into Aegypt: onely he gaue them part of their desire, hee gaue them flesh vntill it became loathsome, that so their Angels food might better relish in their mouthes. And thy louing father will not vtterly withdraw his graces, nor suffer thee to become againe a slaue of the Deuill: only, he will it may be, giue thee ouer to some sinne or other, vntill thou thy selfe shalt loath it, that so his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces might be the better esteemed. The Israelites for their murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings were faine to wander fortie
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:17903:83"/> yeeres in a wildernesse: and thou for thy sins shalt not altogether escape vnpunished. I will not flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thee: if thou wilt serue the Lord, prepare thine heart to temptation; for he chastiseth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery child, whom hee receiueth. But bee not heerewith discoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: though the Israelites wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred forty yeeres in a wildernes, yet did not the comfortable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of their God at any time forsake them: and though thy calamities bee neuer so great, yet assure thy selfe, that as the suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Christ doe abound in thee, so thy consolation shall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound through Christ; <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> and by how much the outward man is corrupted, by so much shall the inward man daily be renued. If thou becommest lame in bodie, thou shalt run the way of Gods commandements more swiftly: if thou fallest into a lower estate,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:17903:83"/> God will giue thee a more lofty minde to contemne this world &amp; worldly things: no sooner was the man cast out of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, <note place="margin">Ioh. 9.</note> but Christ opened him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe more familiarly vnto him. Whatsoeuer thou art, wheresoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thou art, keepe thy Sauiours words, and he and his Father will come, and dwell with thee: thy bodie also shall become the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the holy Ghost. <note place="margin">Ioh. 14. 23.</note> Thus, the whole Trinitie will keep thee companie: the Father and Son will dwell with thee, the holy Ghost will dwell in thee: and is it likely, that God will forsake heauen for thy sake? No, thinke not so: what then (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) will God doe? Surely, he wil bring heauen with him at his comming: thou shalt haue some litle taste of those heauenly ioyes aforehand, as the Israelites had of the fruit of Canaan before
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:17903:84"/> they entred thereinto. Consider with thy selfe: should not the holy Ghost, the true comforter of a godly man, and dwelling within, more inwardly reioyce his heart; than this world, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie to a godly man, and being also without? Beware, that thou bee not in any sort pleased with thy selfe; vntill the assurance of those true and euerlasting ioyes doe more reioyce thine heart; than any of these vaine and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie delights, whether ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, honour, beautie, pastimes, or other worldly vanitie whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion.</hi>
                  </note> Thus haue I now, as one of Gods builders, labored to make thee a Temple of Gods Spirit: and though I haue not beaten with hammers thereabout; yet haue I beaten my braines, as thou seest; if by any meanes thy stonie heart might bee fitted to
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:17903:84"/> this purpose. Heeretofore, the Temple at Ierusalem was Gods house, wherein hee was said to dwell: but since Christs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, God hath chosen the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of his children to bee his Temple. For, <hi>Know yee not</hi> (saith S. Paul) <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 16. &amp; 6. 16.</note>
                  <hi>that your bodie is</hi> (now) <hi>the Temple of God, and that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God dwelleth in you?</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer then a good Christian is, there is the Temple of God; there is the Arke or chest; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ris.</hi>
                  </note> and there within the Arke, are the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles written with the finger of God; for, <note place="margin">Ier. 31.</note>
                  <hi>I will put my Law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts.</hi> How blessed now is the state of a godly man euen in this vale of miserie! For, seeing he alwaies carieth about him the <hi>Tables of the testimonie;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 31.</note> how should hee not sometime haue the testimonie of Gods Spirit vnto his spirit, <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> that he is heire of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:17903:85"/> the kingdome of heauen? Seeing againe, God hath promised to heare those which call vpon him in his holy Temple; <note place="margin">1. King. 8. 29. and 9. 3.</note> how should he not heare a good Christian praying heartily vnto him? For whensoeuer such a man praieth with his heart, he alwaies praieth in the Temple of God: although indeed, if at any time hee praieth with his lips only, let him know, that hee praieth without at the doore, and hath no promise to be heard. Now, I haue endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my selfe, that thou mightest be partaker of this great blessing, as to become the Temple of God himselfe, who is the Lord of Lords, and King of Kings: but if thou vilely esteemest of this high calling, and thereby makest thy selfe vnworthy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; yet this is my comfort, that I am sure not to lose my labour, <hi>For wee are</hi> (saith Paul) <note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.</note>
                  <hi>vnto God</hi>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:17903:85"/>
                  <hi>the sweet sauour of Christ, in them that are saued, and in them that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish: to the one we are the sauour of death, vnto death; and to the other the sauour of life vnto life.</hi> My de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire is, that vnto thee I might be the sauour of life vnto life: for this cause (God knoweth) I haue written. And if for this cause thou hast read likewise; then know, that two things are yet lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto thee. The one, diligent meditation: for it was one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of the cleane beasts, <note place="margin">Leuit. 11</note> to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate or chew the cud. Surely, though there be some hope, that the stonie ground may bee wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red often, &amp; the thorny ground may haue the thornes cut vp: yet if the crowes deuoure the seed, before it taketh any roote downeward; there is no hope at all, that it should bring forth fruit vpward vnto eternall life. The other, continuall prayer:
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:17903:86"/> for Paul that planteth, <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollos that watereth, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; neither is it <note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note>
                  <hi>in him that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, or in him that runneth, but in God that hath mercy.</hi> Aboue all things then forget not that say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Sauiour Christ; <note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note>
                  <hi>Aske, and it shall be giuen you: seeke, and yee shall finde: knocke, and it shalbe opened vnto you.</hi> And now to end in a word. Thou art (I am sure) a man endued with reason: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider then, if Christ first sending his Spirit to knock at the doores of our hearts, wee will not suffer him to enter in: whether it bee not very reasonable, that wee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards knocking at his gate of mercy, he should not open vnto vs neither. Vnlesse God first dwell in thee heere on earth, thou shalt neuer dwell with God in the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:17903:86"/>
               <head>A prayer to the holy Ghost.</head>
               <p>O God the holy Ghost, one God with the Father and Sonne, by whom wee were first created, and hitherto haue been preserued, that we might becom thy Temple, euen an house for thine Honour to dwell in. Come downe (we pray thee) vnto vs, the works of thine owne hands: take possession now of thy Temple, which is ready prepared: we are willing (o Lord) euen now to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine thee; o help (we beseech thee) our vnwillingnesse. And if there be any of vs, which had rather continue a stinking dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of that vncleane Spirit, the Deuill: it is (o Lord) because he doth not know, how sweet and comfortable an house-holder thou art. Breake in then with violence: spare not the house
<pb facs="tcp:17903:87"/> (good Lord) spare not the house: get in euen against his will; and he which is now most loath thou shouldest enter in, shall then bee more loath thou shouldest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part againe. We must needs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge (o most glorious God) that we are an vnfit man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for such a Master: but, doe thou abide in vs, we humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee, that so in some mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure we may be fit. Cleanse thou vs, and we shall be cleane: wash thou vs, and we shall be whiter than the snow. Wee haue one Father, which created vs: wee haue one Sauiour, which redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs: bee thou also one San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifier, which maist dwell in vs continually. That so we, which are many in bodie, may bee all of one minde: and howsoeuer in this world wee be strangers one to another; yet we may be all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether fellow-citizens of the
<pb facs="tcp:17903:87"/> heauenly Ierusalem, there to dwell with our Father, our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and Sanctifier, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. Amen, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Lord God, I acknowledge and confesse, that thou on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly art the author of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse: and if this my enterprise bee good, o prosper then thy handy worke. I can but cast the seed: and through thy grace I haue done what I can. Now this remaineth, that thou (o Lord) which art onely able, shouldest giue encrease. O giue encrease then (I beseech thee) for thy name sake; that so thy power may appeare, which art able to saue by whom thou wilt: and this Readers faith may not bee in the wisdome of men, <note place="margin">1. Cor.</note> but in the power of God. Thus shall
<pb facs="tcp:17903:88"/> thy name (o Lord) which is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glorious, onely bee glorified. Vnto God almightie, who only giueth seed to the sower, and grace to sowe it, and a blessing vnto it being sowen: Vnto God, who onely is all in all things, bee giuen all honour and glory both now and euermore, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17903:88"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>